<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Mr. T.H. late minister: now fugitiue: from Sir Edvvard Hoby Knight. In answere of his first Motiue</title>
            <author>Hoby, Edward, Sir, 1560-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839870</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1177:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Mr. T.H. late minister: now fugitiue: from Sir Edvvard Hoby Knight. In answere of his first Motiue</title>
                  <author>Hoby, Edward, Sir, 1560-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 114, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F[elix] K[ingston] for Ed. Blount and W. Barret, and are to be sold at the signe of the blacke Beare in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Higgons, Theophilus.  First motive of T.H. Maister of Arts, and lately minister, to suspect the integrity of his religion.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659. --  First motive of T.H. Maister of Arts, and lately minister, to suspect the integrity of his religion.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. T. H. LATE MINISTER: Now Fugitiue: FROM SIR EDVVARD HOBY Knight.</p>
            <p>IN ANSWERE OF HIS <hi>first Motiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEBR. 3.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take heed, Brethren, leſt at any time there be in any of you an euill heart, and vnfaithfull, to depart away from the liuing God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>Ed. Blount</hi> and <hi>W. Barret,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the blacke <hi>Beare in Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. v. 17.18.</bibl>
               <p>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, marke them diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, which cauſe diuiſion and offences, contrarie to the doctrine, which you haue learned; and auoid them.</p>
               <p>For they that are ſuch, ſerue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but their owne bellies; and with faire ſpeech, and flattering, deceiue the hearts of the ſimple.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL ROMISH COLLAPSED LADIES, of Great Britanie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ommiſerable Ladies, this my Letter to <hi>M. T. H.</hi> lay a while vpon my hands, for want of a conuenient meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger: at last, by conference with a Merchant of <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> J vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood there was no way ſooner to conuey it to S. <hi>Omers,</hi> then by your Ladiſhips meanes, as hauing weekely newes from the <hi>Engliſh houſe,</hi> which wil hardly admit any ſtranger, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer with her new <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> whom ſhe masketh vnder counterfeit names. Might J therefore be ſecured, by the priuiledge of your fauors, not to haue it intercepted by any <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall</hi> ſuperuiſor, you ſhall giue mee iuſt cauſe to pay you the tribute of my beſt ſeruice.</p>
            <p>J am the bolder to ſolicite you herein, for as much as I firſt came to the view of his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> by one of your neere followers, who gaue
<pb facs="tcp:4329:3"/> me alſo to vnderstand, how great thoſe <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> are in your books. Had I no other thing to write, theſe tidings would yet haue ſet my pen on worke.</p>
            <p>Jn ſooth, my respectiue care of your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare enforceth me exceedingly to grieue, that you, who haue been baptized ſince the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rites were aboliſhed; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeene this inuincible faith now fully ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; being ſo noblie deſcended; and religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trained vp, ſhould ſo prostrate your ſelues to that <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> beast, whoſe ſpotted skin, and alluring ſent leadeth into the den of destruction. I could wiſh his <hi>Seminaries</hi> had leſſe ſubtiltie, or you more constancy. You may wel thinke, were their grounds of ſuch ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as they beare you in hand, they would not ſo buſilie ſwarme about your ſexe, which, by reaſon of your leſſe abilitie of iudgement, is ſoonest inueigled with their wiles. Your own <hi>Prateolus</hi> hath giuen them an hint of the eagernes of your affection, of the pitifulnes of your inclination, what fit instruments you are, both for your ſundrie opportunities, and many intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, to ſerue their turne: ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:4329:3"/> if they once win the night-crow, to ſing their dittie, then make they no doubt, but that the whole houſe will ſoone dance after their pipe.</p>
            <p>Hauing once diued into your ſecrets, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, qualities, and affaires, it cannot be long before they rule the rost: <hi>Scire volunt ſecreta Domus, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> indè timeri:</hi> they wil make you ſure for ſlipping the colar, without ſome great diſaduantage. Jf they find in any of you quicknes of ſpirit, boldnes of ſtomacke, or volubtiltie of ſpeech, ſhe ſhall be employed, as their Agent, (as not long ſince ſome of you haue been, though in vaine, vnto two noble perſonages now deceaſed) to deale with ſuch, whom either croſſes haue distracted, or ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes weakened; where they themſelues can haue no acceſſe: by which meanes their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſpreadeth it ſelfe on euery ſide.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that throughly to poſſeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of your fauour, they will pretermit nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, nor meanes; yea they will not ſtick to ſet out our <hi>Ladies</hi> picture, (as one of your ſprite-ſpeakers did) with one of your best fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if that may gaine your aſſent.</p>
            <p>VVhat will be the iſſue of this your blind
<pb facs="tcp:4329:4"/> and factious zeale, J refer me to your ſelues. Js there any hope you ſhould euer be better reſolued, as long as you must neither pollute your eyes with our bookes, defile your eares with our Sermons, nor grace our Churches with your preſence?</p>
            <p>You much trouble your ſelues about the Antiquitie of our Church, which you are no leſſe vnable to conceiue, then vnwilling to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. J would to God, you would not be wiſe aboue that which is fit: <hi>Quid quod libelli Stoici inter ſericos iacere puluillos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant?</hi> S. Paul teacheth you to <hi>aske</hi> (not to grieue) <hi>your husbands at home.</hi> Salomon would haue you <hi>giue the portion to the houſhold, &amp; the ordinarie to the maids, to open your mouths with wiſdom, and to haue the law of grace in your tongue: Then ſhould your husbands be knowne in the gates, when they ſit amongſt the Elders of the Land.</hi> VVhereas now, being kindled with thoſe helliſh Mercurialists, the flame of this your intemperate zeale preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, nay threatneth the vtter deſolation of your whole ſtocke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:4"/>
            <p>Might it pleaſe you to conſider the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite expence, which theſe chargeable encro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, the <hi>Ieſuitical</hi> drones, ſucke out of your eſtates; your monethlie checker-payments; the danger of forfetting your ioyntures; the incapabilitie of ſuing in any of his Maiesties Courts; the griefe of your neere Allies, and deare friends, for the declining hopes of your ruinous posteritie; or at the least your owne infamie, wherewith you are generally bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, your houſes being held as nurſeries of poiſonous weeds, and pestilent plants; your tenants, and attendants promiſing no great ſafetie to the King, nor peace to the State, nor tranquillitie to the Church: Might it, J ſay, pleaſe you to ponder theſe things aright, it is vnpoſſible you ſhould be ſo inconſiderate, as to buy a fantasticall, J will not ſay, a fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call humour, at ſo high a rate.</p>
            <p>VVhy ſhould you be ſo respectleſſe of thoſe worthy Gentlemen, your huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, as to cauſe their honors to be eclipſed, their loyalty ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and their aduancement hindred, by your recuſancie? How do you think he ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted wiſe, who can no better order his owne
<pb facs="tcp:4329:5"/> houſe? How ſhould he be held fit for gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the State, who cannot bring thoſe that are ſo neere him to the conformitie of the Church?</p>
            <p>How theſe things may affect you, J can not tell: happily as you generallie diſtaſte all that is not of your owne ſtampe, you will paſſe them ouer, with a diſdainefulleie, ſtill <hi>ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelues with your owne works, and going a whoring with your owne inuentions.</hi> Herein ſhall you more harme your ſelues, then hurt me, who for my friendly aduertiſement deſire no other be one, then the deliuerie of this letter encloſed. <hi>Fare you well.</hi> From my houſe in the <hi>Blackfriars.</hi> May <hi>20. 1609.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Hoby.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4329:5"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. T.H. LATE MINISTER, NOW FVGITIVE: FROM SIR EDVVARD HOBY Knight, in anſwer <hi>of his first Motiue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter <hi>Theophilus Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons;</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. cap. 12. v. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Faciendi plures libros nullus est finis: There is none end in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many bookes:</hi> and as <hi>Plures,</hi> ſo no age euer afforded <hi>tam inermes &amp; inertes,</hi> as this doth: among which I lighted vpon a book of yours, entituled, <hi>The first Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of</hi> T. H. <hi>Master of Artes, and lately Minister, &amp;c.</hi> Wherein, had you not bin an <note n="b" place="margin">Lamiae domi caecae, foris oculatae.</note> ouer partiall beholder of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of your owne fantaſtical wit, you could not but haue ſeene, that the defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie thereof, deſerued rather to haue it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4329:6"/> troden vnder the <note n="c" place="margin">Proles vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea pedibus conculcanda, non manibus gestanda.</note> feet, then hatched, or harboured in the boſome of thoſe (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>vnfortunate</hi>) Ladies, vnto whom it was by your factious factors ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vented. Such is the miſhapen <note n="*" place="margin">Vnus in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, nullus <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a ſingulis, rudis indigestaque moles.</note> diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion therof, that your former <note n="d" place="margin">Imprinted at London 1608.</note> 
               <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasticall examination of mans iniquitie and Gods iustice,</hi> taketh it in foule ſcorne, to haue it reputed for her ſiſter. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, of that, you may ſay, with the <note n="e" place="margin">Of his faire pictures, and foule children.</note> Painter, <hi>Luce pinxi;</hi> of this, <hi>Nocte finxi,</hi> there is ſuch beautie in the one, and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in the other.</p>
            <p>For my owne part, hardly could I be induced to beleeue, but that the name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Printer did much wrong, in fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it vpon a man, borne of parents ſo religious, in the raigne of a <hi>Queene</hi> ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, bred in an <note n="f" place="margin">Oxford.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie</hi> of that fame, and graced by a <note n="g" place="margin">Of London.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> of that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend eſteeme. But ſince your own claime doth chalenge it, <note n="h" place="margin">Peut. Heut. de lib. hom. Nat.</note> 
               <hi>Partus ventrem ſequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> you muſt looke to maintaine it, or elſe it will lie vpon the pariſh, of <hi>Romiſh Jeſuites.</hi> To bee ſure to disburthen our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4329:6"/> ſelues, as ſoone as it was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, I diſpatched this paper, as my <hi>Borſholder,</hi> to conuey it from text to text, from argument to argument, from Father to Father, vntil it come to the firſt motiue, where it was firſt farrowed.</p>
            <p>And haue you any reaſon to look for any further or extraordinarie kindneſſe at my hands? Do you thinke, I can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie forget, what ſparkes haue flowen out of that forge, where you now are become a needie <hi>Vulcanian</hi> apprentice? Can the horror of that diſmal proiect, that <hi>Gunpowder</hi> plot,<note n="i" place="margin">Iudgement of a Catholike Eng. § 1.</note> howſoeuer ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed ouer with <hi>Parallels,</hi> (the eternall ſtaine of your murtherous profeſſion) but ſtill liuely repreſent before me, euen in my dreames, and imprint in my moſt ſerious thoughts, that furious <note n="k" place="margin">Vna dies da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit exitio, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per annos ſustentata ruet moles &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china regni. <hi>Lucret.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Blast,</hi> which my ſelfe, (my poore ſelfe) ſhould haue ſenſiblie felt, or my good friends at leaſt bewailed?</p>
            <p>No no <hi>(M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Theomiſus,)</hi> for ill doth <note n="l" place="margin">E Paulo Saul.</note> 
               <hi>Theophilus</hi> fit you, I ſhould regiſter it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my capitall and dreadfull ſinnes, if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4329:7"/> I do not my vtmoſt with ſword and pen to reuenge it. Oft haue they been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in cauſes of leſſe moment, and therfore ſeeing <note n="m" place="margin">Velleius Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terc.</note> 
               <hi>ineuitabilis fatorum vis,</hi> the diuine prouidence of my <hi>God,</hi> hath reſerued me from the <hi>Bedlome</hi> violence of your rage, I hold the little remainder of my Pilgrimage moſt worthily ſpent in freeing all poore weak inueigled La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and other my deare countrimen from your <hi>Syrenicall</hi> deceit. Neuer can the moſt ſuperlatiue <hi>(Parliament)</hi> ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie be accounted extremitie in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting or ſharpeſt reſearch of that viperous brood, thoſe mercileſſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, among whom you are now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triculated; <hi>Quibus ipſa miſericordia (me viuo) nunquam ignoſceret:</hi> whom mercy it ſelfe ſhould be thought cruell euer to forgiue. <note n="n" place="margin">Stulta est cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia, peritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro parcere <hi>funi.</hi>
               </note> Execution in theſe caſes were better then diſputation. How gladly I would ſee the one, may appeare by my forward attempt of the other. And were it not that <hi>Protestant charitie</hi> giueth a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to my pen, I would vow neuer to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4329:7"/> forgiue the immanitie of thoſe match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſcreants,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matth. 12.32.</hi> id est:</p>
                  <p>Ante leues ergo paſcentur in aethere cerui &amp;c.</p>
               </note> vntill I heare their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution pronounced by the mouth of the moſt ſupreame Iudge. Let him make the caſe his owne, that cenſureth me of too much bitternes: <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf could not deny <note n="p" place="margin">Iob. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Pellem pro pelle,</hi> that all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a man hath, hee would giue for his life. I muſt confeſſe, I did euer before ſuſpect the cariage, but then did I begin <note n="q" place="margin">Nam quis iniquae tam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens <hi>Romae,</hi> tam ferreus vt teneat ſe? <hi>Iuuen.</hi>
               </note> irreconciliablie to deteſt all the Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries of your <hi>Romiſh</hi> forge.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee <hi>(M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Theomiſus) vbi meus me calceus vrget.</hi> Iudge you, if I haue not iuſt cauſe to be an eternall oppoſite to all of your coate, I meane, to al ſuch Engliſh fugitiues as haue been borne ſince the bleſſed raigne of our late (&amp; euer deare) <hi>Angelicall Q. Elizabeth,</hi> and fallen from the Apoſtolicall, Catholique, <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 1.8. As it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtood vnpolluted by the Biſhop of Rome.</note> 
               <hi>Romane</hi> faith by her eſtabliſhed. I am not (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) a Miniſter, nor <note n="ſ" place="margin">S. Dunſtons London.</note> 
               <hi>Lecturer,</hi> as you were; yet muſt I, according to the ſmall meaſure of my indowments, ſhew my ſelfe a <note n="t" place="margin">Etiam cum ſanguine &amp; ſudore.</note> 
               <hi>Christian,</hi> in withſtanding the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4329:8"/> moſt inſolent oppugners, of that faith, into which I was <hi>Baptiſed,</hi> and whereof <hi>King James</hi> my moſt <hi>Dread Soueraigne</hi> Lord and Maſter is Defender. And albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it I am not in holy orders my ſelfe, yet will I do my beſt to order you, and the rather, that you may no longer be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch to <hi>Christs Church,</hi> whereof you were once a member, in that famous <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie,</hi> wherein by their vndeſerued fauour, I was M. of Arts, and <hi>(abſit inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia verbo) Senior</hi> of the <hi>Act,</hi> before your mothers wombe did beare ſo monſtrous a burthen as your ſelfe. In ſumme, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is to reclaime you, that you periſh not, my purpoſe is to confute you, or at leaſt to diſcouer you, that you ſeduce not, and my readines is alwaies preſt to anſwere you, or any <hi>Fugitiue Romified Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado</hi> whomſoeuer.</p>
            <p>In this my diſcuſſe, albeit I can hardly ſtay my ſelfe, from encountering the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall particulars, and cutting off all the heads of your <hi>Hydra,</hi> yet becauſe there are many valerous and worthie <hi>Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4329:8"/> Qui ſeuertores Muſas colunt,</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">D. <hi>Morton</hi> Deane of Gloceſter. D. <hi>Field.</hi>
               </note> whom it doth nearer concerne, as being yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, to anſwere for themſelues, whoſe learning is no whit appayled, nor cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage daunted, to iuſtifie the trueth, and cleere your pretended deprauati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their owne writings, I will, (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whatſoeuer concerneth them,) confine my ſelfe within this liſt. My whole diſcourſe ſhal conſiſt of ſix <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffes.</hi> In the firſt, <hi>The cauſe of your Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall be ſifted.</hi> In the ſecond, <hi>Your maine reaſon for Purgatorie diſproued.</hi> In the third, <hi>your Prime father anſwered.</hi> In the fourth, <hi>your Prime Proteſtant D. Humfrey defended.</hi> In the fift, <hi>The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Poſition maintained.</hi> And in the laſt, <hi>A friendly retreate ſounded.</hi> So that by that time I haue done, <hi>obſtinacie</hi> it ſelfe, ſhall I hope, confeſſe that, our <note n="x" place="margin">Pſalm. 48.2.</note> 
               <hi>Sion is faire in ſituation, the ioy of the whole earth, and the city of the great King:</hi> whom I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech vpon the knees of my hart, for his deere Sons ſake, <hi>Vt praeueniat inſpirando, adiuuet proſequendo, finiat benedicendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4329:9"/>
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Naturaliſtes, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other obſeruable relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, record this of the <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Struthio ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melus.</hi> Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius in Geneſ. cap. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>329.</hi> n. <hi>71.</hi> Bercor. Redus. moral. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>69.</hi> vide Plin.</note> 
                  <hi>Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thio,</hi> that hauing once put her head into the buſh, albeit her whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die bee out, yet ſhee thinketh her ſelfe, cloſe and ſafe, as if ſhe were cleane out of ſight. The like perſwaſion, as it ſeemes, hath bred the ſame witleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in you. The cauſe of your reuolt is couered ouer with ſuch glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, weightie conſiderations, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant detections of falſhoods in our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Proteſtants, that forſooth <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 96. <hi>&amp;</hi> 97</note> 
                  <hi>Morall reaſon</hi> muſt aſſure vs, you were not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by any light or ſudden motion; that you would not ſtriue vnwiſely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the benefits of fortune; or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly againſt the dutie of nature, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſome ſuperiour and more excellent <hi>Conſideration,</hi> did obtaine a powerable authority in your ſoule. Theſe furze are, in your conceit, a ſufficient ſhelter to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4329:9"/> keepe your hypocriſie from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried. But, alas, howſoeuer you thruſt your firſt <hi>Motiue</hi> into this thicket, the buſhes, God wot, are too bare to couer ſo vaſt &amp; monſtrous vntrueths, which lie open to the view of the world. Such is the waight of that lumpiſh maſſe, that it is vnpoſſible for your <hi>Struthio's</hi> wings to ſoare out of our reach. It is no new fallacie to come in, with a <hi>non cauſa vt cauſa;</hi> it was of yore a logicall axiome, <hi>Quaedam videntur &amp; non ſunt:</hi> you haue now made it practicall: wherein you iumpe with your predeceſſors the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Phariſes, as in opening of this your painted ſepulchre will more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. It ſtandeth not with my nature, I confeſſe, to blaſe your ſhame, neither is my profeſſion to be an hiſtorian to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of your ranke, yet rather than the integritie of ſo well founded a <hi>Religion,</hi> (then which none better) ſhould receiue the leaſt blemiſh by your forged calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, it is fit the world ſhould be better acquainted with that malignant humor
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4329:10"/> which hath driuen you into theſe fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke fits. All diſeaſes, by the verdite of the beſt Phyſitions, ariſe <hi>vel ex repletio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, vel ex inanitione,</hi> either from fulneſſe, or emptineſſe: to the like originall we may alſo refer the diſtemperature of the minde. Plentie breedeth ſenſualitie, and luxurious affections: want is the mother of hereſie, and ſchiſmaticall defections. And no maruell, for they that faſt much are vſually troubled with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertigo,</hi> the ſwimming and giddineſſe of the braine. This was <hi>Aërius</hi> his diſeaſe: whoſe emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtomacke being diſappointed of the fat <note n="c" place="margin">Aug. de hereſ. n. <hi>53.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Biſhopricke,</hi> after which he did long gape, ſent vp ſuch foggie myſts of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment into his daſeled head, that like the <note n="d" place="margin">Mat 17.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Demoniake</hi> in the Goſpell, hee fell ſometimes into the water, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the fire, neuer ceaſing to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble downe the hill of faith, vntill he fell flat <hi>Arrian.</hi> Aſpiring ſpirits, hauing their hopes defeated, growe turbulent, and that, either to bee reuenged of thoſe, whoſe fauours haue been more nigard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4329:10"/> then their prodigall deſires, or to raiſe a new fabricke for their better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes vpon the vantage of <note n="e" place="margin">Haec non ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit, aliam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>an ur vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>am.</note> 
                  <hi>oppoſition.</hi> It much grieueth mee to reade of any ſpice of this diſeaſe in men of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but more to ſee it in men of the Church, and moſt of all, that they who are thus tainted, do rather lay the fault vpon the infallible groundes of a ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les religion, than vpon the boundleſſe appetite of their owne endleſſe deſires, making conſcience the ladder of their climing ambition.</p>
               <p>Doe you aske me <hi>Quorſum haec?</hi> I will tell you, <hi>Mutato nomine de te narratur fabula.</hi> When I ſpeake of <hi>Aërius,</hi> I thinke of him whom indeed I am loth to name, euen of M. <hi>Theomiſus:</hi> I might call you M. <note n="f" place="margin">Plautus.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſurio:</hi> for ſo do the <note n="g" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>g. de hereſ. n. <hi>69.</hi>
                  </note> ſymptomes bewray your malladie, <hi>Si ſaturio fuiſſes, non Circumcellio fuiſſes.</hi> Faine would I plucke back my pen, but that my eye tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth me how you haue plaide the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, in aſcribing your reuolt to the inſoliditie of our religion, which was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4329:11"/> wholly hammered by your owne ill ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced diſcretion. It is twentie to one, but ſome of your Ladies will be pearing into this letter, therefore will I write no more, then I am able to iuſtifie, nor will I put you in mind of anything, wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your owne knowledge ſhall not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſubſcribe. If any thing be omitted, it is not my ignorance, but my charitie that concealeth it. Theſe things were not done in a <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 26.26.</note> 
                  <hi>corner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That famous Colledge of <hi>Christs Church in Oxford,</hi> which you haue ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paied, for the ſweete milke which you haue ſucked out of her breaſts, hath not yet forgotten how you were euer ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>Puritaniſme,</hi> how violently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe you were to all ſuch, as were ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to fauour the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Sea. She doth yet ſmile to think, what paine you took, being <hi>Cenſor</hi> of the houſe, in putting your hand to the ſawing downe of a poore harmeleſſe <hi>May-pole,</hi> becauſe you thought it came out of a <hi>Romiſh</hi> forreſt. When you were <hi>Lecturer</hi> at S. <hi>Dunstons,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4329:11"/> your contributorie auditors thought your long prayer, and ſpitting pawles too ſhort, becauſe the reuerend Biſhops (yea euen your own Lord and Maſter) were euer left out for wranglers and <hi>Antichristian Hierarchies,</hi> not worthie to be named in the ſame day, with your holy Paſtors and ſanctiſted Miniſters. Thus haue you euer affected ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <p>But how commeth it to paſſe, you ſhould now fall into the oppoſite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie? <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <p>Dum vitant ſtulti vitia, in contraria cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</p>
                     <p>Incidit in Scil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam &amp;c.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Jn vitium ducit Culpae fuga, ſi caret arte.</hi> Is there no meanes betweene <hi>Niceneſſe</hi> and <hi>Nastineſſe?</hi> was the faith wherein you were ſo long trained, ſo weake as that one <note n="k" place="margin">Diſſuendae non diſc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>candae ſunt ami<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>itiae. Omnis ſubita mutatio peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> blaſt hath ouer-throwne it all? haue you bin thus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, by the <note n="l" place="margin">In the title.</note> detectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of falſhoods in our learned <hi>Protestants?</hi> Did you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with them for ſatisfaction, and they not able to reſolue you? then would your <hi>Apologie</hi> paſſe more currant.</p>
               <p>You mention onely their writings, wherein you play <hi>Canis ad Nilum,</hi> cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4329:12"/> and ſnatching heere and there, for fragme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſentences, which, like <note n="m" place="margin">Artic. 12. ſect. 6. applied by you, pag. 122.</note> 
                  <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els Procustes,</hi> you ſtretch out to the length of your owne fancie: plainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying your ſelfe, that either you were not ſo well grounded, or ſo throughly affected to your Religion, as it became an inſtructer of others, or that to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie your ſelfe, and gaine the more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with thoſe, vnto whoſe harber you were driuen by the tempeſtuous ſtorme of your extremities, you did picke theſe imaginarie cauillations; which had they been reall doubts indeed, might with your greater credit and charitie, haue been decided in a more priuate ſceane. Hee that hath but halfe an eye may ſee there is a Pad in the ſtraw: happily you haue done this, either wholly to eſcape, or to agree the better with your credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that ſeeing your ſudden alienation, their deſperate debts may be more eaſily compounded: happily hauing miſſed a former preferment, you thinke by this meanes to be wooed by the State to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4329:12"/> to your firſt loue: happily the yoke of wedlocke being ſomewhat burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to your ſhoulders, was an induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make you caſt off the <note n="n" place="margin">Luk 9.62. You haue plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ananias,</hi> fortune be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held you not with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigne and comfortable aſpect, as you pretend. pag. 97.</note> 
                  <hi>Plough.</hi> Surely not only ſome, but euen all of theſe were the cords, that haled on your <hi>First motiue.</hi> Your debts were (the world knoweth) very clamorous: the miſſe of your preferment was grieuous: and the mariage-god <hi>Himenaeus</hi> was none of your beſt friends. To eaſe your ſelfe of all theſe, which <hi>Atlas</hi> himſelfe could hardly vndergo, you thought good to caſt anchor in a new ſea, and to fiſh in troubled waters.</p>
               <p>And for as much as you could not be well rid of your wife, creditors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grieuances, as long as you held your profeſſion, you choſe rather with <note n="o" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Himenaeus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> to make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of this, then to haue your ſhip o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged with thoſe. The Ieſuites, you knew, were no ordinary guls, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if you ment to be <hi>Sanctuariſed</hi> by them, it lay you in hand firſt, <hi>Auaere ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4329:13"/> carcere dignum,</hi> to aſcertaine them by ſome audacious proiect, of your fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fidelitie: as you haue now done, by making your owne pen a croſſe-barre of reſtraint, for any welcome returne vnto your old home. Into what a pitifull ſtraight (poore ſoule) were you then driuen? was there no other way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire your ruinous fortunes, but by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a bill of diuorce vnto that faith, whereunto you were firſt vnited? it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, it cannot, howſoeuer you pretend, but <note n="p" place="margin">Coelum non animum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant qui trans mare currunt.</note> grieue you to the heart, that you haue with <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſold your birth-right for a meſſe of pottage, which many teares will hardly redeeme. I cannot blame you,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Richard Etkins</hi> houſhold Chaplaine vnto the now Lord Biſhop of London.</note> if at the ſight of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>R. E.</hi> your old fellow Chaplaine and friend, you had <hi>Peters</hi> teares in your eyes, for the denial of your Maſter. I do eaſily belieue, vpon his credible report, that at ſuch time as he deſired your companie to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> or to <hi>England,</hi> you ſmote your hand vpon your heart, and in great paſſion vttered theſe words, <hi>O that I might ſafely returne,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4329:13"/> for that is my deſire.</hi> The ſmall liking you haue to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, you ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie manifeſted, when as being recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to that <hi>Synagogue,</hi> by one <hi>Flud</hi> a Prieſt, you did yet after your returne out of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> write a little Pamphlet of <hi>veniall</hi> and <hi>mortall</hi> ſinnes, flat againſt the principles of that profeſſion. And were you not now in <hi>Hucksters</hi> hands, whoſe vigilent eies haue mewed you faſt vp, in their idolatrous cage, I dare ſay you had been in <hi>England</hi> long ſince, for ſo did you proteſt, as you hoped to haue any part in the paſſion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, that within three weeks at the furtheſt, (if you liued ſo long) you would bee heere after your fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: who, good man, tooke a tedious iourney to ſeeke out his loſt ſonne, who neuer opened his mouth to aske him bleſſing for his paines.</p>
               <p>Was it not griefe enough, trow you, to the old man, to ſee his ſonne <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Higgons,</hi> turned into <hi>Thomas Foster,</hi> as if you had been aſhamed to anſwere to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4329:14"/> your fathers name? to ſee you ſo ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie habited, ſo barely arrayed, ſo gaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie viſaged, whom he had ſo carefullie tendred? Was not this griefe enough, I ſay, but that you muſt depriue him alſo of that priuate dutie, which was due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him? and contrarie to his expreſſe commandement, and requeſt, and your owne ſolemne promiſe made to him, make his preſence knowne to your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> wherby he might haue bin in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as much as in you lay, to haue loſt, not only his vnnaturall ſon, but euen his deareſt life in a ſtrange Land? and that which is worſt, make him a ſorrowfull witneſſe of your periurous vow? The like ſolemne oath did you take in the preſence of him, by whom your father was accompanied, that vpon the <note n="q" place="margin">Fides Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica, fides Puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith of a Romane Catholike,</hi> and, <hi>as you hoped to be ſaued,</hi> this booke of yours, which you then ſhewed him, ſhould not be printed. This albeit it be no ſtrange newes to your afflicted wife, and ſome of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued creditors, who are throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4329:14"/> with many ſuch your volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; intended periuries, (as vpon your next replie ſhall bee more particularlie ſpecified, vnder whoſe name ſoeuer you meane to couer it); yet is it a ſufficient teſtimonie, that not the approbation of your <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, but the grimme aſpect of your owne eſtate, hath driuen you to this exigent. It is not long ſince you haue complained, through impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent emulation &amp; ambition, (both which do diſtract the mind, and turne it ouer to helliſh diſcontent) that if you might haue been then preferred, and not adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed rather to returne to the Vniuerſitie, to repaire your wings; you would not haue changed your copie ſo ſoone, nor made ſo ſorie a flight from vs to <hi>Rome.</hi> This you know to be well knowne, and vpon further occaſion may bee better ſpecified vnto the world. <hi>Hinc illae la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae.</hi> And yet as if <hi>D. Humfrey</hi> had made you fall out with your wife, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, creditors and all, you are ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently ſhameleſſe, as to ſay, <note n="r" place="margin">Pag. 172.</note> 
                  <hi>He that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4329:15"/>
"was the ſnare of death vnto many, began to "looſe the ſnare wherein I was intangled.</hi> Whereas you ſhould more truelie and tolerablie haue ſaid, of your expected preferment, <hi>Quod alteri beneficium, mihi fuit maleficium,</hi> that which was another mans bliſſe, was my Bane.</p>
               <p>Let any man now iudge, whether you be not infected with <hi>Aërius</hi> his diſeaſe. Doe you not now ſtand vpon the like tearmes with our religion, as mony-mongers do with their courted miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? <hi>Auge Dotem</hi> wil make vp the match. She that hath no portion, hath little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in your eies. Well may you li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your ſelfe to the young <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pag. 99.</note> 
                  <hi>Partridge,</hi> you are ſo <hi>Pragmaticall,</hi> that you would faine flie to aduancement, the ſhell yet vpon your head. Had you loued our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as well as <hi>Iacob</hi> did his <hi>Rachel,</hi> you would not haue thought much, to haue ſerued ſeuen, and ſeuen yeeres, for her ſake. Put as if the Lord had no more bleſſings, then one, you are like a reed ſhaken in the wind, impatient of delaies,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4329:15"/> ſtorming to waite the good pleaſure of his will:
<q>
                     <l>Flectere ſi nequeas ſuperos, Acheronta mouebis:</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If there be not a golden mine in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, you will trie what you can finde by digging into the ſuburbs of hell. But be you well aſſured, <hi>Denarij ſepulchrales, Pluto's,</hi> (I ſhould haue ſaid S. <hi>Peters</hi>) Pence, will neuer paie your debts, nor make vp the remainder of your wiues portion, the loſſe wherof hath made her miſſe of your loue. You ſhall be kept, I dare warrant, as hungrie as a hauke, that they may haue you ſtill at their lure. Thoſe golden mountaines, that <hi>Flud</hi> promiſed, will prooue no better then mole-hils of droſſe: which in the end your compulſarie imploiments muſt be faine to purchaſe, with the expence of your beſt blood. What can your tongue or pen refuſe to do for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vpon whom you muſt whollie depend? You haue alreadie, being but a Punie in their Schoole, made ſo deſperate an aſſault, not only againſt our Church, but euen
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4329:16"/> gouernment of our State, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be ſoone ſet a work, about ſome more deſperate and dangerous attempt. What wil they not expect fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, whoſe pen hath already broched this <hi>traiterous</hi> and ſeditious aſſertion? <note n="t" place="margin">Pag. 163. and 164.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That in your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts you could not but acquit the Papists from the crime of diſobedience, and vndutifulnes to the State: for as much as they made not themſelues contrarie to it, but it is made contrarie to them; the <note n="*" place="margin">Non tellus cymbam, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurem cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba relinquit.</note> change be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the State, which propoundeth a new faith, and not in them who conſerue the old.</hi>
                  </q> A graue and religious ſentence. Hell it ſelfe could not haue belched out anie more peſtilent. But why ſhould we take it vnkindlie at your hands? You vſe our State no worſe, then you did your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor our Church more vnkindlie, then your owne wife: hauing withheld your naturall dutie from the one, and your loyall affection from the other. If theſe be the fruits of your religion, I am ſo farre from enuying it, that my verie ſoule abhorreth it.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4329:16"/>
               <p>If anie man now ſay of you, <note n="u" place="margin">Pag. 98.</note> as you put the caſe, <q>
                     <hi>He did run well, who did let him, that he obeyed not the truth?</hi>
                  </q> He ſhall not need to run to Saint <hi>Omers</hi> for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he may thus reſolue his owne doubt, that you were a louer of your ſelfe, more then a <note n="x" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Louer of God:</hi> that you were a <note n="y" place="margin">Iames 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>wauering minded man, and vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in al your waies:</hi> that you were in the <note n="z" place="margin">Act. 8.23.</note> 
                  <hi>gall of bitterneſſe,</hi> and in the <hi>bond of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie;</hi> and that, to returne your owne <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 99.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>phraſe, you maske intolerable falſhood, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed vnder the ſhape of ſinceritie &amp; truth.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For my owne part, (and herein haue I been ſeconded, with better and more noble iudgements) I could neuer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe, that the multiplicitie of <hi>Schools,</hi> needleſſe <hi>Lecturers,</hi> and trencher <hi>Schoole-masters,</hi> would ſort to any better effect. For the firſt it is a naturall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that too many <hi>ſiences</hi> weaken the ſtate of the Tree: &amp; ſome haue thought, that the parochial endowments, and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiate preferment of this Land, are by the tenth part too little, to afford ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4329:17"/> ioyce, to thoſe infinite ſuperficiall ſtudents, who, were it not for this vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of ſchooles, might much more profitablie be brought vp in ſome other profeſſions and trades. For the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <note n="b" place="margin">Maxima hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticorum pars nimis maturè ex ſcholis ad pulpita alioſuè gradus euoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Alan. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. pag. 106.</hi>
                  </note> were thoſe men, continued in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſities,</hi> till they had ſome compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſetled liuings void for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abroad, they would no doubt be better groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and more firmelie minded. But when euerie nice dame muſt haue a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dante</hi> at home, who muſt vaniſh at her frowne, if my yong maſter be ſomewhat, as ſhee thinketh, ouer diſciplined; and when euerie iching-eared congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will, beſides their learned <note n="c" place="margin">Nemo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta in patria ſua.</note> 
                  <hi>Pastor,</hi> be ſerued with an humorizing <hi>Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> whoſe diuinitie muſt ſpout, as oft as they turne the cocke; as being more then ſeruillie obliged to their voluntarie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, then are theſe diſtracted minds compelled to bethinke themſelues what courſe they ſhall take, for their liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, when either my miſtreſſes diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or the approach of ſome new and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4329:17"/> more zealous Orator, telleth them that they muſt bee put out of their ſteward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips: then will they be glad to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in forren houſes: they are for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie coaſt, vpon which the wind driueth them; or if they ſit idle <hi>(nihil turbarum machinantes,)</hi> it is becauſe <hi>Nemo condux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it:</hi> No man hired them. This conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, was that motiue which made you ſit downe and write, <note n="d" place="margin">Like the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt ſteward.</note> thirtie for ſixtie, and fiftie for an hundred, making what reckoning you pleaſed of our religion, as if it were to bee rated according to the valuation of your partiall pen: which, to currie fauour for a new ſeruice, was now ready to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whatſoeuer was ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the old.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4329:18"/>
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing thus diſmaſked your hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, &amp; vncaſed your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſhip of your Lions skin, I know no reaſon but that I may take hart of grace, and venture vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Maine</hi> reaſon for the proofe of <hi>Purgatorie.</hi> What ſaid I? your <hi>Maine</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? admit it were as <hi>Maine</hi> as it is <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> yet, I muſt deale truly with you, had euerie bird his owne <note n="a" place="margin">Moueret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicula riſum.</note> feather, your Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cockes plumes would ſoone vaniſh. For indeed, it doth rather both for matter and manner appertaine to <note n="b" place="margin">Vpon the ſame Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Mat 12. and Marke 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Maldonat,</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Vpon the ſame Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Mat 12. and Marke 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ianſenius,</hi> and <note n="d" place="margin">Bellarm. de Purg. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sic oculos, ſic ille manus, ſic ora gerebat:</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>So is it by them propounded, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. Wherein you ſecretlie bewray the inualiditie thereof: For why ſhould you be ſo ſaucie, as to wreſt this weapon out of their hands, vnleſſe you meant to handle it better then they? indeed, <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum refert quid à</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Dauus nè an herus?</note> 
                  <hi>quoque dicatur,</hi> and for ought I ſee, your thruſt is as ſhort as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4329:18"/> theirs; wherefore you muſt be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue your old <hi>Venie</hi> put off, with an old ward.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Sic disputas egregie Magister: VVho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall ſpeake a word against the holy Ghost, it ſhall not bee forgiuen him in this world, nor in the world to come. Ergo, Some ſins are forgiuen in the world to come.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Purgatorie.</hi> Ergo, <note n="f" place="margin">Each im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this <hi>per modum ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> that <hi>per modum cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae.</hi> pag. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Prayer for the Dead.</hi>
                  </q> This is your <hi>Lactea <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ia,</hi> your <hi>Aurea Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tena,</hi> with which you are ſo fettered to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſect. Well, be as proud of it as you will, I dare auerre, it hath but one good linke, as for the reſt, the teſt ſhall proue them not ſo good as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginian</hi> oare: affording not ſo much as a S. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas penie</hi> towards your <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> nor a taper for your <hi>Dirge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was an old prouerb when I went to ſchoole, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritas non quaerit angulos:</hi> How commeth it to paſſe, that S. <hi>Marke</hi> his expoſition is ſuch a mote in your eie, that it galleth you to the quicke to haue him decide this controuerſie? Did hee not write of the ſame matter? Was hee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4329:19"/> not indued with the ſame ſpirit? it may be trulie ſaid of them both, as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 41.8.</note> 
                  <hi>prophetically</hi> foretold, <hi>one Deepe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth another.</hi> They were both prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by the two <note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 25.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Cherubins,</hi> one behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the other. <hi>Matthew is excellently</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by <hi>Marke, Marke notablie</hi> ſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled by <hi>Matthew.</hi> Let the queſtion be this: <q>
                     <hi>VVhen ſhall he that ſinneth against the holy Ghost be forgiuen? S. Marke maketh anſwere,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ergo</hi> no ſimple gloſſe. pag. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Neuer.</hi> Which is all one, as if he had ſaid with S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> more figuratiuelie, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>Neither in this world, nor in the world to come.</hi>
                  </q> Implying nothing elſe, but the perpetuitie of the puniſhment, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding no ſpecificall diſtribution of ſinnes, whereof ſome are to be remitted in this world, and ſome in the world to come, as you ſuppoſe. For ſo S. <hi>Marke</hi> explaineth himſelfe, &amp; his fellow Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, altogether as largely as S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> in theſe words, <note n="k" place="margin">Mark. 3.29.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>is culpable of eternal damnation:</hi> So that <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes partatiue,</hi> and <hi>Markes collectiue</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:4329:19"/> doe note one thing, <hi>viz. Eternitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were you, as you pretend, a true child of Antiquitie, you would not bee more curious then <hi>Athanaſius, Jerom, Hilarie,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as often as they examined theſe words, to render them by <hi>Aeternum,</hi> not ſeeking any further.<note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> This was <hi>no ſimple gloſſe</hi> in thoſe daies. The Greeke Fathers dreamed not of temporall puniſhment after death, but of eternall. And this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth with the opinion of <note n="m" place="margin">Caluin. Harm. Euang. in eum locum.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluin,</hi> who holdeth that the ſcope of the text concerneth onely the laſt iudgement, where there is no place for the remiſſion of any ſinne, which was not formerlie pardoned in this life. Now then, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee ought to attribute more faith to your affirmitiue collection, or to Saint <hi>Markes</hi> Identicall narration, iudge you. The ſyllogiſticall examination of your argument, wil make the folly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of more euident. <hi>VVhoſoeuer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it ſhall not be forgiuen him in this world, nor in the world to come:</hi> Ergo (ſay you) <hi>Some ſinnes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4329:20"/> are pardoned in the world to come.</hi> That you may ſee how willing I am to giue <hi>Sea-roome,</hi> for feare of ſplitting your tender ſided <hi>Foyst,</hi> I will grant all, and yet, <hi>Nè canas ante victoriam.</hi> For your <hi>Purgatorie</hi> ſhould notwithſtanding bee verie impudent to intrude it ſelfe. <q>What <note n="n" place="margin">You may wel ſay, what is this to Purgatorie? pag. 19.</note> inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience ſhould follow, if I ſhould yeeld that <hi>ſome ſins</hi> are pardoned in the world to come?</q> I dare auouch it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any preiudice to the cauſe. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſpeaking of the <hi>vnbeleeuer,</hi> ſaith, <note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>He is condemned alreadie,</hi> and yet you cannot denie, but that he muſt come to a ſecond <note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Doome.</hi> So is it with the <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer:</hi> albeit he haue full <note n="q" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Remiſſion</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his pardon ſealed in this life, yet he muſt haue the ſame proclaimed at the <hi>Generall Gayole deliuerie</hi> in the world to come. In which ſenſe he may as truly be ſaid, to haue his ſinnes then pardoned, as the other his then condemned.</p>
               <p>The words of your ground import as much, <hi>Non remittetur eis in hoc ſeculo:</hi> viz. <hi>per Remiſſionis applicationem, nec in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4329:20"/> viz. <hi>per Remiſſionis promulgationem.</hi> That is, they ſhall not haue the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſurance of remiſſion in this world, wherewith the elect of God haue their conſciences <note n="r" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſealed, neither ſhall they haue the fruition thereof</hi> in the world to come, into which the children of God are to be inducted. <hi>Nec hîc Spem: Nec ibi Rem.</hi> Neither preſent expectation, nor future poſſeſſion. So that as ſome ſins are there puniſhed, ſo alſo there are ſome there pardoned, &amp; yet your <hi>Purgatory</hi> cleane excluded. If you ſay this expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth either diſagree with the ſcope of the place, or analogie of faith, I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bee better informed, by ſoliditie of reaſon, not ſuperfluitie of words. For as yet I cannot ſee, but that it rather fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <hi>à contrario,</hi> thus: <hi>This remiſſible ſin ſhall neither be forgiuen in this world, nor in the world to come,</hi> Ergo, <hi>This or that remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſin ſhall be forgiuen, both in this world, and in the world to come: the two latter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing added as inſeparable adherents to the former.</hi> And ſo the ſinne is heere exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4329:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> by oppoſition to other ſins, in the depriuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that double benefit, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of other ſinners, that are penitent, are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable: vnto both which, hee that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt the holy Ghoſt can lay no claime.</p>
               <p>I will not vie too faſt, it may be you keepe the <hi>Fiue-finger</hi> in your hand for the laſt tricke; when you come in with your, <hi>Ergo, ſome ſinnes remiſſible, are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in the world to come,</hi> happilie you haue this mentall reſeruation, viz. <hi>which are not formerly forgiuen in this world.</hi> I proteſt I thought as much. You haue turned vp. <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quae ligata manent in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ea posteà non ſoluuntur.</hi> Matth. 16.19.18.18. Ioh. 20.22.</p>
                     <p>In the place that the tree falleth, there it ſhall be. Eccleſ. 11.3.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nodie.</hi> But <hi>dic ſodes,</hi> deale plainlie with your friends. Came this card out of the ſtocke? Is there any ſuch clauſe in the text? or any other expreſſe Scripture, to iuſtifie this inſertion? A yong gameſter may ſee that this is but a bad ſequele, <hi>The ſin against the holy Ghost, ſhall neither be forgiuen in this world, nor in the world to come:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Some ſins are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in the world to come, which are not forgiuen in this world.</hi> Heere is old pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4329:21"/> but I will diſcouer you. A Kentiſh Gentleman, not purpoſing to make his heire a great Clerke, ſaith thus: <hi>My eldeſt ſon ſhal neuer be ſtudent in Oxford, nor Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge:</hi> were he not an excellent <hi>Artist,</hi> trow you, that ſhould hence infer, <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſome of his other ſons ſhall go to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> In this there is no neceſſitie, the Gentlemans ſcope being, by this <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> diſtribution of the Engliſh <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> to ſhew he meant to ſet his ſonne in ſome other courſe, and not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to determine, what he would doe with the reſt. Or if he ſhould ſay, (as he may well without <note n="t" place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ridiculous abſurditie) My ſon ſhall neither be ſcholar of Eton, nor fellow of Kings Colledge:</hi> were he not out of his wits that would hence conclude, Ergo, <hi>A man may be</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt foundation.</note> 
                  <hi>fellow of Kings Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that was neuer ſcholar of Eton?</hi> In this there is no <hi>Poſſibilitie.</hi> I am ſure it was a rule, when I firſt haunted <note n="x" place="margin">An exerciſe in Oxford Schoole-ſtreets for yong ſcholars, Logicians.</note> 
                  <hi>Paruies, Quod de vno negatur, non ſemper de diuerſis affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur, &amp; è contra.</hi> My reaſon is this, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test idem Praedicatum, de diuerſis ſubiectis
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4329:22"/> rectè Praedicari:</hi> as thus: This propoſition is true, <hi>Eos qui foris ſunt Deus iudicabit:</hi> and this as true, <hi>Eos qui intùs ſunt iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit Deus,</hi> where <hi>Subiectum</hi> doth differ, the <hi>Praedicatum</hi> being all one: Neither may wee argue thus, <hi>They are to bee iudged by God,</hi> Ergo, <hi>not by the Magistrate:</hi> This were an <hi>Anabaptistical</hi> hereſie. Common ſenſe will diſproue it, and yet you ſticke not to conclude, <hi>The ſinne against the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost ſhal neuer be forgiuen in this world, "nor in the world to come,</hi> Ergo, <note n="y" place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Some ſins "ſhall be forgiuen in the world to come.</hi> It will put you to a foule plunge, if I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort your owne <hi>Paralogiſme</hi> vpon you: Thus, <hi>The ſin against the holy Ghost,</hi> ſhall neither be remitted, <hi>Quoad culpam, aut quoad poenam,</hi> in this world, nor in the world to come; Ergo, <hi>Some ſinne ſhall be remitted, &amp; quoad culpam, &amp; quoad poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, in the world to come;</hi> which is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the poſition of your owne ſect, recorded <note n="z" place="margin">Tom. <hi>4.</hi> dist. <hi>45. §. 1.</hi> p. <hi>557.</hi>
                  </note> by <hi>Suares, Contingit peccata mortalia remitti in ſeculo futuro, quod non potest intelligi de Remiſſione quoad culpam,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4329:22"/> Ergo neceſſariò intelligendum est quoad poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi> It happeneth that mortall ſinnes be forgiuen in the world to come, which cannot be vnderſtood of the forgiuenes of guilt, therefore neceſſarily to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Which you dare not allow in reſpect of <hi>Guilt,</hi> and yet the text doth as equallie intend Remiſſion of guilt, as of puniſhment. Which your <hi>Caietan</hi> confeſſeth, ſaying,<note n="a" place="margin">Caietan. in cum locum.</note> 
                  <hi>De peccato aſſeritur, non remittetur in hoc ſeculo, vt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligamus comprehendi non ſolum remiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem poenae ſed culpae: Peccatum enim nomen est culpae.</hi> Thus are you hampered in your owne ſnare; <hi>Miſerè perit, qui ſuis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis perit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I feare I am ſomewhat too quick with <note n="b" place="margin">Turpe est vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere iacentem.</note> you: it ſeemeth by this your wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted collection, you are yet to learne the rule of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Jn Con. de fil.</note> 
                  <hi>In certis quibuſdam generibus negationum, vbi quid de vna qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam re negatur, non mox diuerſum affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, et ſi talem quandam ſpeciem prae ſeferat.</hi> You muſt not alwaies gather an affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue out of a Negatiue, though at the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4329:23"/> firſt ſight it may ſeeme to bee implied. As if I ſhould ſay, <hi>Christ was deliuered to death, not for his owne, but our ſinnes,</hi> were hee now any better then a cauelling <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phister,</hi> who would hence gather, <hi>Ergo Christus habuit peccata?</hi> Therefore Chriſt had ſins of his owne, becauſe it was ſaid, <hi>not for his owne?</hi> The Apoſtle writing to <hi>Titus,</hi> ſaith, <note n="d" place="margin">Chap. 3. v. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Not by the workes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which we had done, but according to his owne mercie he ſaued vs:</hi> neither doth he intimate, howſoeuer the phraſe may ſeeme to beare it, that wee of our ſelues had done any workes of righteouſneſſe at all. And ſo heere, <hi>Simpliciter negat: Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ponit;</hi> by a figuratiue, and diſtributiue partition of the two parts of Eternitie, he exaggerateth their puniſhment, who ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, ſaying, <hi>That they ſhal not be forgiuen in this world, nor in the world to come:</hi> and doth not, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the rule of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely determine the contrarie of other mortall ſinnes.</p>
               <p>But alas poore ſoule, how can I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4329:23"/> blame your weaknes, when your learned maſter, <hi>Bellarm.</hi> is grauelled in the ſame ſands? When <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> obiecteth, it is no good <hi>Logicke</hi> to argue affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie from a <hi>Negatiue,</hi> as thus: <hi>Philip King of Spaine,</hi> is not King of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> Ergo, there is a King of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians,</hi> he is driuen to this ſhamefull ſhift, <note n="e" place="margin">Bellar. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Purg. cap. <hi>4.</hi> §. Respon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, non. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondeo, non ſequi ſecundùm Regulas Diale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticorum, &amp; tamen ſequi ſecundùm Regulas Prudentiae, quià alioquin faceremus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ineptiſſimè loquutum:</hi> It followeth not (ſaith he) according to the rules of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke,</hi> but according to the rules of<note n="f" place="margin">You would faine be <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi> Ape. pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie,</hi> for otherwiſe there muſt needs be an <hi>abſurditie</hi> in the Lords ſpeech. As if that could by any wiſe man be allowed for <hi>Neceſſarie,</hi> which by <hi>Logicall</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is not <hi>Neceſſarily deducted</hi> out of the Premiſſes.</p>
               <p>And why ſhould the ſpeech, vttered by way of exaggeration, ſeeme ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde and vnprobable as you terme it? Shall your owne <hi>Maldonat</hi> bee an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator between vs? Scholying vpon theſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4329:24"/> words of <hi>Matth. 19.14. Jt ſhall be eaſier for a Camel to go thorow the eye of a needle, then for a rich man,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="g" place="margin">Maldonat. ſuper Matth. <hi>19.14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Haec oratio homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus abſurda videtur qui non intelligunt,</hi> &amp;c. This ſpeech ſeemeth abſurde to thoſe which vnderſtand it not, &amp;c. ſo that the abſurdity in the popular vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, doth not diminiſh the truth, or authority thereof. Why then ſhould this prouerbiall amplification ſound ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couthly in your eares? You would bee loath I ſhould ſerue you with a <hi>Non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligis,</hi> vnder <hi>Maldonats</hi> ſeale. What if I ſhould ſay, I would not allow <hi>Theomiſus</hi> to be my ſchoole-maſter, either quicke or dead? Do I therefore intend that you can reade me a ſchiſmaticall lecture, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am in my graue? No, but my meaning by this hyperbolicall exaggeration is, that I would neuer admit you to that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, albeit, it were poſſible that I could be capable of your <hi>Romiſh</hi> charmes. So that it is now needleſſe to debate, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your owne inſtance of the<note n="h" place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>barren woman,</hi> (which may emphatically be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4329:24"/> 
                  <hi>ſecundùm morem vulgi)</hi> be more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, or the idle author thereof fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous.</p>
               <p>This one thing I will yet adde, if the like coniecturall collections ſhould be vrged againſt you, wee ſhould ſurely heare of iniurious dealing. There is no one place more familiar among you, then this of <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Matth. 1.25.</note> 
                  <hi>But hee knew her not vntill ſhe had brought forth her first borne Sonne.</hi> If out of this we ſhould come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note n="k" place="margin">Non ouum ouo ſimilius.</note> you, Ergo, hee knew her after ſhee had borne him, or, Ergo, ſhe had more ſonnes, you would thinke that bleſſed and holy Virgin to bee moſt irrecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſably <note n="l" place="margin">Vt Antidico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanae. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lench. haer. p. <hi>133. 6.</hi> vel Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidij blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia. Aug. de Eccleſiast. dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. ca. <hi>68.</hi>
                  </note> diſparaged: and yet <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vntil,</hi> ſeemeth to imply the firſt, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the first borne,</hi> to import the ſecond. To o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen my ſelfe, I confeſſe freely my reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend eſteem of that <hi>ſacred Virgin</hi> is ſuch, that I ſhould ſtop my eares, if ſuch diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants would not ſtop their mouthes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things, this ſeemeth to mee very ſtrange, that glorying ſo much in the authoritie, and <note n="m" place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> commending the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4329:25"/> indifferencie of the Fathers, you haue omitted <hi>Origens</hi> opinion, whoſe anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie would haue greatly ſteaded you in this caſe. Then had you ſtrucken the naile on the head, there had been no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion: we ſhould haue bin glad to compound. I confeſſe freely, he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth the ſame note out of theſe words of your ground, <hi>Eſſe in altero ſeculo</hi> 
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <p>Hoc est con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Origenem, qui dicit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes veniam conſequuturos post vniuerſale iudicium, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actis multis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis.</p>
                     <p>Hug. Cardin. in Mat. fol. <hi>42.</hi> b.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionem,</hi> &amp;c. And that this might bee thought a veniall encrochment vpon the text, hee goeth further, breaking downe all the Lords fences, that the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels</hi> and <hi>damned ſpirits</hi> might enter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in this <hi>after-pardon,</hi> entituling them to that Remiſſion, which ſhall be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the world to come. Heere is good ſtuffe. <hi>Qui ſemel verecundiae fines tranſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, eum gnauiter eſſe impudentem oportet.</hi> Ouer ſhooes ouer bootes. If the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world ſhould giue you <hi>Origens</hi> inch, a whole ell of abſurdities would not ſerue your turne. We ſhould euerie day haue <hi>Postes</hi> out of <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> and ſuch ſtore of <hi>Graue</hi>-miracles, that it would
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4329:25"/> make a <note n="o" place="margin">Yea <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> deuout mare. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Eucha. cap.</hi> 8.</note> horſe to breake his halter to ſee them.</p>
               <p>Far more Analogicall is Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostoms</hi> expoſition, <hi>Jt ſhall not be forgiuen in this world, nor in the world to come,</hi> that is, ſaith he, <note n="p" place="margin">In Matth. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Non effugient poenam:</hi> They ſhall bee ſurely puniſhed in this world, and in the world to come. And this ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with verie good <note n="q" place="margin">Non remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur hîc vel alibi, ſed &amp; hîc &amp; alibi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nietur. Theoph. in Matth.</note> reaſon: as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe proueth by this induction: <hi>Some</hi> ſinners are puniſhed only in this life, as that inceſtuous <note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Corinthian, that his ſpirit might be ſaued in the day of our Lord Jeſus: ſome</hi> only in the life to come, as the rich <note n="ſ" place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Glutton,</hi> who while hee was aliue had the world at will: and <hi>ſome</hi> were ſinners in graine, (as I may tearme them,) &amp; are both tortured in this life, and tormented in the life to come, as the <hi>Sodomites</hi> who had heere <hi>ignem</hi> 
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſulfureum,</hi> and haue there <hi>ignem infernalem.</hi> So that when our Sauiour heere, denouncing againſt theſe Capitall malefactors, telleth them that their ſinnes ſhall neither be forgiuen in this world, nor in the world to come, it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4329:26"/> is as much as if he ſhould ſay, they ſhall both ſmart for it in this world, and rue it in the world to come. Whereof, (not to ſpeake of <hi>Judas,</hi> patroniſed by <note n="u" place="margin">De Justif. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine)</hi> we haue a liuely, though fearefull, preſident in the miſerable end of that curſed Apoſtata <note n="x" place="margin">Vicisti Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilae.</note> 
                  <hi>Julianus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would now gladlie ſee, what fault you can find with this holſome expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it tendeth to godlines, in ſetting out the horror of that fearefull ſinne, which our Sauiour heere laboureth to beate downe in the blaſphemous Pharaſaicall Scribes, and the truth thereof is euident by the former inſtance: wheras your illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſetteth open a wide gap to carnall libertie, our <note n="y" place="margin">Maxima pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi illecebra impunitatis ſpes.</note> nature being ſo prone to defer the time of our conuerſion, vpon the leaſt hope of future remedy. Neither is it backed by any expreſſe teſtimonie of holy writ, nor any exemplary proofe, beſides your <hi>Hobgoblins, Rawheads, Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die-bones,</hi> and <hi>Night-ghosts,</hi> which the world hath now for many yeares ſince forgotten to beleeue.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4329:26"/>
               <p>You will be tride by the Fathers, you ſay. A good motion. My reaſon teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me to reuerence them, my religion forbiddeth me to adore them: my lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure will not ſerue to ſearch or cite them all. Can you except againſt <hi>Athanaſius?</hi> Let him be the Vmpire, he hath written a whole Tract of this ſubiect, which will put all out of doubt. If you can find one line in him for this your expoſition, <hi>My eye ſhall enter an action against my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> Nay I will yet go further, there is not one of the ancient Fathers, <note n="z" place="margin">Vbi benè ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo melius, vbi malè nemo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius.</note> (<hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> excepted) vnto <hi>Augustines</hi> time, who euer made any ſuch gloſſe. As for <hi>Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Jerom, Chryſostome, Theophylact,</hi> and my arbitrator <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> they will not I am ſure, lend you one ſuch ſyllable to ſaue your life. No maruell then, if by the validitie of this text, you were ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully led to the <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> approbation of this doctrine. Theſe you will ſay are but my words, and therefore for your better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation peruſe them.</p>
               <p>By this you may ſee, (if the muffler of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4329:27"/> 
                  <hi>Superstition,</hi> hath not cleane hoodwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked your eyes) the weaknes of your firſt ground: Well, when you haue ſpent all your forces in the maintenance of this fort, it will proue but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſtrife about words,</hi> which the <note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.4.</note> Apoſtle appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to ſuch as account gaine (I will not ſay <hi>Purgatorie</hi>) to bee godlineſſe. No doubt, your talent and time might much more profitablie be ſpent, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>in doctrine according to godlines.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you may perceiue how willing I am to ſatisfie you to the full, I will doe my beſt endeuour to remoue that ſcruple, which the authoritie of that great Father, and worthie Diuine S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> ſeemeth to haue firſt faſtned in your wauering thoughts: wherein I ſhal finde the leſſe difficultie, for as much as your ſelfe confeſſe of all thoſe of his ranke, <q>that<note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Though they were men of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable valew, yet they were not exempt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4329:27"/> from the errors of infirmitie</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Spero te minimè mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riturum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum. Epiph. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostomo. Spero te in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam minimè rediturum. Chryſost. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanio. Socrat. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>attending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the condition of mankinde:</hi> and, <hi>That they may erre</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Secundùm Analogiam loci.</hi>
                  </q> Which, were I captious, might bring this with the reſt of your teſtimonies, being meere expoſitions vpon your former ground, into ſome doubt. For when hee ſaid, <note n="d" place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>The prayer of the Church is heard for ſome men deceaſed out of the world;</hi>
                  </q> leſt hee might be vrged with a <hi>Proba,</hi> he giueth this reaſon, <q>
                     <hi>For it could not be ſaid truly of ſome men, that their ſinnes ſhould not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen in this world, nor in the world to come, vnleſſe there ſhould be ſome men, who though they are not pardoned in this world, yet they ſhould bee pardoned in the world to come.</hi>
                  </q> What is this with thoſe other of <hi>Gregory, Jſidore, Beda,</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> by you cited, but expoſitions vpon the ſame place? wherein you confeſſe they may erre. And indeede I wonder you will bee ſo friendly, as to grant that they may miſſe the cuſhion in the <hi>Analogie</hi> of the place. Little do you think what may be thence inferred. I would faine know what is the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4329:28"/> ground of faith? Is it not <hi>the word?</hi> This word hath diuers parcels: now if they miſtake in the Analogie of one place, (as you grant) why not then as well in another? and ſo you couertly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict your ſelf by implying, <hi>They may erre, Secundùm Analogiam Fidei, in the Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of faith.</hi> Thus haue you made thoſe bleſſed <hi>Fathers</hi> much beholding vnto you.</p>
               <p>But that I may merit to be kalendred "by you among thoſe that are of a <note n="e" place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>more "candide and honorable dispoſition,</hi> I wil not preſſe you ſo neere. God knoweth, I haue no pleaſure to diminiſh the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſteeme of their ſacred pens. Wherfore for the place cited out of the <note n="f" place="margin">Pag. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>incomparable worke,</hi> of that holy <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> with whom you firſt conſulted, giue me leaue, I pray you, to put you in minde of what your owne <hi>Viues</hi> hath formerly told you, writing vpon theſe words, which you haue heere alleaged, he ſaith thus: <note n="g" place="margin">Super Aug. de ciuitat. Dei. lib. <hi>21.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In antiquis libris Brugenſi, &amp; Colonienſi, non leguntur iſti decem aut
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4329:28"/> duodecim qui ſequuntur verſus, neque in exemplaribus Friburgi excuſis.</hi> And it is true hee ſaith, They are not in any our knowne Copies to be found. Thus hath your owne man <hi>Viues</hi> tripped vp the heeles of your grand authoritie, and laid your <hi>first Motiue</hi> in the duſt. But I muſt doe you no wrong, he goeth a ſtep fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaith, <hi>Forſan non deſunt in alijs: Perhaps other impreſſions haue them.</hi> And ſo your <hi>Ponderous</hi> reſolution, both for this interpretation of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ſaid <hi>Fathers</hi> iudgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Purgatory,</hi> hangeth vpon a weak thred, vpon a <hi>Forſan, Perhaps,</hi> which is as good as a <hi>new nothing</hi> to hang vpon your ſleeue. Thus as you haue but one <hi>Ground,</hi> and that wreſted, ſo it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth your <hi>Prime</hi> father may be ſuppoſed to be forged. Which may giue vs iuſt cauſe to miſtruſt the like double dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the reſt.</p>
               <p>Hauing hitherto buſied my pen, in ſounding the depth of your hypocriſie: in cleering your firſt <hi>ſcripture</hi> from your
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4329:29"/> Sophiſtrie: in defending your <hi>Prime Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> from your forgerie: I muſt now ſhew my ſelfe a dead-mans Champion, in freeing your <hi>Prime Protestant Doctor</hi> from your Calumnie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Gregiam vero laudem, &amp; ſpolia amplatulisti, Tu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> liber<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuus.</hi> Alas what will become of our <hi>Religion?</hi> our poore Church muſt needs totter, the <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 168. and 140.</note> 
                  <hi>Pillars</hi> thereof being ſo miſerablie ſhaken. Had you the <hi>Jaw-bone</hi> of an Aſſe in your hand, who were able to ſtand before you, our beſt worthies being ſo deadly wounded with your <hi>Gooſe-quill?</hi> Amongſt the reſt, <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam vellis Leoni Mortuo.</hi> You trample vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dead <hi>D. Humfrey,</hi> as if you would cruſh him to peeces. They that ſuruiue had need to looke to themſelues, your furie is ſo enraged toward the dead. And is it poſſible, that that holy man ſhould ſpend ſo many yeeres, diue into ſo many learned Authors, read ſo many memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4329:29"/> Lectures, and now come to bee taxed by an obſcure <q>
                     <hi>Neoterique</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">Vide ad Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. &amp; pag. <hi>38 82. 168. 169. 172.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
                     <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignitie,2</hi> 
                     <hi>artificiall colluſion,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 
                     <hi>inſolent mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> 
                     <hi>egregious falſhoods,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> 
                     <hi>Rhetoricall flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> 
                     <hi>vnprofitable Rhetorique,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> 
                     <hi>vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſes,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> 
                     <hi>obſcure and vncertaine ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> for <hi rend="sup">9</hi> 
                     <hi>deluſion in his ambiguities,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">10</hi> 
                     <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe in his relations,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">11</hi> 
                     <hi>digreſſions from his matter,</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">12</hi> 
                     <hi>and generall imbecillitie in his diſcourſe. Bona verba quaeſo.</hi>
                  </q> You muſt not thinke to carrie it away with your big lookes. If your curriſh pen be ſo ſhameleſſe as to dare <hi>Mingere in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trios cineres,</hi> be you aſſured the good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers demerits will not permit any true <hi>Oxonian</hi> to leaue his <hi>Orphane works</hi> to the wild world. Let others do as they ſhal ſee cauſe. Far is it from my thoughts, that this my ſhort &amp; rude Letter ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe anie other more ſolid ſupplie. As he did benefit many being aliue, ſo is it fit he ſhould bee defended by manie being dead. It is fit, I ſay, that the debt, which the Church oweth to his <hi>reuerend memorie,</hi> ſhould be paid by men of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4329:30"/> Church. Neither yet are priuate men to burie his particular fauours, with his breathleſſe corps in one ſame <hi>Graue.</hi> It is vſuallie ſeene amongſt baſe minds, <hi>Cum quis Domo effertur, aufertur Gratia.</hi> But ſtill ſhall he lie intombed in my beſt thoughts, who ripened the buds of my yonger ſtudies, with the gladſome raies of his beſt encouragements. Or ſhall I be ſo meale-mouthed, as to ſuffer anie railing <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> to ſooth himſelfe in his diſgrace? Then might my worthie, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and religious <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <p>Elizab. La. Ruſſell Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Euripid.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mother</hi> thinke my time and her coſt altogether miſpent, if in all that time I did not learne to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his repute, by whom ſhee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood I was ſo much honored. And if your ſuperſtition teach you to pray for the dead, you cannot, I hope, blame my generous diſpoſition, to patronize the <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle. 7.37.</hi> Mortuo non prohibeas gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</note> 
                  <hi>Dead.</hi> Full well may I vndertake this combate, without any feare of the foile. I haue peruſed his booke, examined his aſſertions, and weighed his arguments, vpon which view I find you muſt be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4329:30"/> to offer a paire of golden eies to the <hi>Ladie of</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Sichem, <hi>or</hi> Hal <hi>is nearer</hi> S. Omers.</note> 
                  <hi>Loretto,</hi> that you may recouer your ſight, which you haue ſo weakened with ouerſtudying your ſelfe, in the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> that you cannot ſee the <hi>VVood for trees.</hi> You crie out, let him be condemned <hi>for deluſion, depraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. yea but firſt, by your leaue, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Theomiſus,</hi> there muſt be enquirie, <hi>Quid mali fecit? VVhat euil hath he done?</hi> Vpon this triall, I doubt not but this ſentence will be giuen by an indifferent Iudge, <hi>J find no fault in the man, of theſe things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is heere accuſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt grieuance taken againſt this worthie <hi>Doctor</hi> (which is made your firſt warrant, for the triall of your cauſe by the <hi>Fathers</hi>) is this, that he draweth his anſwere to <hi>Campian,</hi> to a concluſion with this ſentence, <note n="f" place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Traſilaus in a mad humour, tooke all the ſhips which he beheld in the Attique hauen to be his owne, though hee poſſeſſed not any veſſell: Such is the frencie of the Romanists, yea greater alſo, becauſe they ſee, and yet ſeeing they diſſemble, that they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4329:31"/> are destitute of all defence from the Fathers.</hi> This you terme <hi>a vast and a notable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth.</hi> If your words might paſſe for ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, it were ſo indeed. But is it poſſible you ſhould ſo ſoone forget, what iſſued from your owne pen, not foure leaues before? How did you there plaie <hi>Traſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> vaunting like a ſecond <hi>Thraſo,</hi> of S. <hi>Aug.</hi> authority in the expoſition of your grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? Wel, what was the iſſue? Did not <hi>D. Humfrey</hi> propheſie right? your own <hi>Viues,</hi> as I ſhewed you, bloweth all away with a <hi>Non leguntur.</hi> Where is now the ſhip you challenged for your owne? It hath but a <hi>Forſan,</hi> a verie thinne planke to keepe you from ſinking. If you a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice haue learned this tricke alreadie, what ſhall we thinke of thoſe, that haue been ſeuen, nay twice ſeuen yeares ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſes to the trade? By that time you haue been ſo long a Practitioner, you will haue twentie ſuch iugling trickes at your fingers ends. It is vnpleaſing to you, I dare ſaie, to ſee your ſelfe taken in the manner, wherfore I will returne in a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4329:31"/> word to the iuſtifying of <hi>D. H.</hi> aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>It will bee verie tedious to ſet before you, the whole ſumme of that pithie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, to <hi>Campians</hi> fifth reaſon <hi>De patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Ab ouo vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad mala.</hi> Which if you iudiciallie peruſe, you ſhall ſee he had good reaſon, after ſo great promiſes, and ſmall performances on his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries part, to conclude as he did. In the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of that ſubiect, <hi>Campian</hi> would faine make the world beleeue, that our Church had quite depoſed the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, and doctors, and that if we would make triall by them, our cauſe were inſtantlie gone. <hi>Omnes nostri ſunt,</hi> (ſaith he in effect) <hi>All the ſhips on the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique ſhore, all the Fathers are ours: The day is ours.</hi> Vnto this challenge, our <hi>D.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth this anſwere, <hi>Nos horum patrum auctoritatem ſolummodò veneramur, nos ad horum Synedrion ſacro ſanctum prouocamus. They alone ſhall bee our Iudges, wee will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to them.</hi> And againe, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erè ac propriè nostros patres in terris vocamus Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4329:32"/> &amp; Apostolos, patres non à patre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trato, ſed à patre patrum delectos.</hi> Wee account them our fathers, whom the <hi>Father of heauen</hi> hath ſet ouer vs. All the exception he maketh againſt the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge is this: <hi>Jncipit</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ab au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reae aetatis heroibus, &amp; à patribus maiorum gentium, ſed mox ad alios vel aenei vel ferrei ſeculi homines deſcendit, quos in vnum quaſi globum ſine vllo diſcrimine coniungit.</hi> This is our D. reſolution; hee is willing to ſtand to the iudgement of the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Primitiue fathers, adding only this, that hee maketh a difference betweene thoſe of the <note n="g" place="margin">Jnter patres. &amp; paterculos.</note> golden age, and thoſe which ſucceed in the braſen and iron age of the world, which the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and leproſie of <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſuperſtition hath ſowred and infected. Now how farre your Challengers right commeth ſhort of his claime, the conference of both their writings will more fullie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, then the breuitie of a letter will permit. And in this behalfe I had rather referre you to a knowne <note n="h" place="margin">Printed at <hi>London</hi> 1608.</note> Sermon, (yet
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4329:32"/> ſo farre as I can learne vnanſwered) that was preached at <hi>Pauls Croſſe, Febr.</hi> 13. 1607: wherein it will appeare, at leaſt in twentie points, how little countenance you haue from thoſe holy fathers, with whoſe names your frothie diſcourſes are ſo ſtuffed, and your controuerſies bombaſted. I am not now an opponent, to vrge the particulars, wherein you proue deſtitute of thoſe Fathers, who are ſtill at your pens end: I ſhall hold it ſufficient, if I can at this time aſſoile that worthie father from your wrongfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations.</p>
               <p>Firſt for his euaſion: <hi>Campian</hi> had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, <hi>The inuiſibilitie of our Church,</hi> and that we ſtood only at the <hi>reuerſion</hi> of <hi>Aë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilantius,</hi> &amp;c. for ſome peſtiferous fragments: Now <hi>D. H.</hi> not knowing how to winde himſelfe out of this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, is driuen (as you ſay) to ſlip col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thus. <hi>VVherein Aerius did erre, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect it; wherin he held any thing agreeable to the Scripture, we receiue it. And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this point of prayer for the dead, we and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4329:33"/> our Church will not digreſſe from Aërius.</hi> I would wiſh none of my friends to open his mouth againſt the leaſt <hi>Retainer</hi> to <hi>Purgatorie.</hi> Belzebub himſelfe ſhall finde more fauour at your hands then ſuch a man. What? Becauſe the Diuels <note n="i" place="margin">Mark. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> that Ieſus was the Sonne of God, will you therefore abiure it, and blot it out of your <hi>Creed?</hi> If <hi>Aërius</hi> (howſoeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe erroneous) doe ioyne with the Primitiue Church, in nullifying obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the dead, will you therefore haue our Church ſo nice, as in a ſtomack to maintaine the contrarie? Had <hi>D. H.</hi> ſaid <hi>Aërius</hi> diſliked them, <hi>Ergo,</hi> wee will not entertaine them: then had he giuen the queſtion to his aduerſarie, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of our Churches Antiquitie, this had bin indeed to picke the crums that had fallen from his table. But becauſe <hi>Aërius</hi> an Heretique was of this opinion, that therfore it is a new coined doctrine, and a diſgrace for our church to hold it, our <hi>D.</hi> thought it no good conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. In matters of this kind wee are not to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4329:33"/> conſider <hi>Quis,</hi> but <hi>Quid:</hi> not <hi>VVho,</hi> it is, or <hi>by whom,</hi> this or that point is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, but <hi>Quid,</hi> what it is that is held. If the perſon be an <note n="k" place="margin">Galath. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Angell,</hi> we haue our warrant to refuſe him, if he bring <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, any thing beſides that which the word warranteth: on the contrarie, if the doctrine be, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that which is written,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>agreeable to that which we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,</hi> though the perſon be an infernall ſpirit that vttereth it, yet he is not to be refuſed. What were this, but with the <note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 76.</note> 
                  <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and <hi>Brownists</hi> (as you ſay) to frequent no Church, becauſe there is ſome blemiſh in euerie Church? were he not a wiſe minter that refuſeth gold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is much droſſe? though there be much chaffe in the heape, yet will not the husbandman forſake his wheate; ſhall the <hi>Arian</hi> hereſie of <hi>Aëri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> make thoſe other truthes which hee held, to be of leſſe eſteeme? By this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we ſhould not haue had one article of our faith left many hundred yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, if, becauſe of mens errors in ſome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4329:34"/> points, we ſhould therfore diſſent from them in all. What cauſe is there then, why I ſhould not highly extol this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſaying of that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enerable man? VVee are not aſhamed to ioyne with Aërius,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>where Aërius ioyneth with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Obſerue this, I pray you, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth it, not becauſe <hi>Aërius</hi> ſaith it is true, but becauſe that is true which <hi>Aë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> ſaith, therefore he beleeueth it. Yea ſhould a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred <hi>Councels</hi> of <hi>Romiſh Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſaicall Scribes</hi> condemne him as an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique, yet were he no whit leſſe to bee followed, in that wherein he followeth the <hi>VVord.</hi> Call you this an <hi>Euaſion,</hi> to hold that which is agreeable to the <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word?</hi> Indeed whatſoeuer diſtaſteth your quaint humors, is an euaſion. Wel, all the aduantage you get by ſuch euaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you may put into your eie, and ſee neuer a whit the worſe.</p>
               <p>Neither is the <hi>Colluſion,</hi> with which he is charged, of any more moment then the former: the words of our <hi>D.</hi> are theſe: <hi>Non improbamus nos quod ſenſit Aë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4329:34"/> &amp; Augustinus retulit, non oportere nos orare, vel oblationem offerre pro mortuis, quia nullo Scripturae dicto continetur: quod &amp; Aug. ſignificare videtur quando hanc commendationem mortuorum dicit, veterem eſſe eccleſiae conſuetudinem:</hi> We do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue that which <hi>Aërius</hi> taught, and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> hath related, that we ought not to pray nor offer oblation for the dead, becauſe this is not contained in any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the <hi>Scripture:</hi> which <hi>Augustine</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doth ſeeme to ſignifie, when he ſaith that this commendation of the dead was an ancient cuſtome of the Church. This you take to bee a ſubtill <hi>Colluſion.</hi> For whereas our <hi>D.</hi> pretendeth, that S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> had only <hi>Custome</hi> to maintaine it, yet you find that he alledgeth Scripture in defence thereof, <hi>For we reade</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the booke of the Machabes, that Sacrifice was offred for the dead.</hi> If this be the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> you build vpon, our <hi>D.</hi> may ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Nullo Scripturae dicto continetur:</hi> it is not contained in any precept of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> As hauing formerly proued out of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4329:35"/>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Rat. pr. pag. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aquinas, Antoninus,</hi> and <hi>Jerome,</hi> that thoſe bookes of <hi>Machabees</hi> are not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall. Neither is it our <hi>D.</hi> ſurmiſe, that <hi>August.</hi> ſeemeth to ſignifie as much, who elſewhere doth plainly and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minablie conclude, that they are not <hi>Diuini Canonis.</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Aug. de mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Jn Machabaeorum libris, etſi aliquid mirabilium numero inſerendum conuenientiùs ordini fuiſſe inueniatur, de hoc tamen nulla cura fatigabimur, quia tantùm agere propoſuimus, vt de diuini Canonis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilibus exiguam historicam expoſitionem tangeremus.</hi> Where he confeſſeth, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he might wel haue produced ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for his purpoſe out of the <hi>Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees,</hi> yet becauſe he meant to deale only with ſuch <hi>mirables</hi> as were of the <hi>Diuine Canon,</hi> hee would not trouble himſelfe with thoſe, as thinking them vnfit to ſtand cheeke by ioule with the other.</p>
               <p>The ſame Father writing againſt <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Epist.</hi> ſaith thus, <note n="o" place="margin">Contra Gaud. Epist. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Machabaeorum Scriptura recepta est ab eccleſia non inutili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſi ſobriè legatur, vel audiatur, maximè propter istos Martyres; ſed ob hanc cauſam
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4329:35"/> in Canone morum, non Fidei cenſeri poſſet.</hi> Shewing that there muſt great ſobrietie be vſed, in the hearing and reading of thoſe bookes, and that they are in the Canon of Manners, and not of faith. And againe, <hi>Jn ſanctis Canonicis libris, nuſquam nobis diuinitus praeceptum, permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumue reperiri potest, vt velipſius adipiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae immortalitatis, vel vllius carendi cauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diue mali, cauſa, vt</hi> 
                  <note n="p" place="margin">2. Machab. 14.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Razis ſeipſum occidens laudatur.</hi> In the holie Canonicall books, there is no diuine precept, or permiſſion to be found, that we may, either to gaine immortalitie, or to eſcape any perill, make away with our ſelues, as <hi>Razis</hi> did, and is therefore commended in the <hi>Machabees.</hi> Where is now the <hi>Colluſion?</hi> Doth not S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſeeme to ſignifie as much? <hi>Lyra</hi> is as liable to the cenſure of <hi>Colluſion,</hi> who auerreth <note n="q" place="margin">Praefat. in Tob. <hi>as he is cited by our</hi> Lubbertus, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> de Princip. dogm.</note> that they are receiued of the Church, to be read for the information of manners. <hi>Brito</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the ſame mind, <note n="r" place="margin">Jn prolog. Machab. <hi>cited by</hi> Lubbert. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Libri Machabaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non ſunt in Canone, &amp; tamen leguntur in Eccleſia, per conſtitutionem Romanae ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae.</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:4329:36"/> The bookes of <hi>Machabees</hi> are not in the <hi>Canon,</hi> and yet they are read by the conſtitution of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church. I might cite <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ad reg. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douicum. Lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Rabanus,</hi> &amp; diuers others, but <note n="t" place="margin">Jn fine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. ad hist. vet. Teſt. <hi>as he is cited by our</hi> Lubbertus quo ſupra. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Caietan</hi> ſhall ſerue for all: <hi>Ne turbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Nouitie, ſi alicubi reperias libros istos inter Canonicos ſupputari, vel in ſacris Concilijs, vel in ſacris Doctoribus: Non autem ſunt Canonici, id est, Regulares ad firmandum ea quae ſunt Fidei. Poſſunt tamen Canonici, id eſt, Regulares dici, ad aedificationem fidelium, vtpote in Canone Bibliae ad hoc recepti. Cum hac distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione poteris diſcernere dicta Augustini, &amp; ſcripta in Concilio prouinciali Carthaginen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi.</hi> Trouble not thy ſelfe, if thou find thoſe books, either in the ſacred Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, or holy Fathers, to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that are <hi>Canonicall,</hi> for they are not Canonicall, that is, <hi>Regular,</hi> to ground thoſe things that appertaine to faith, albeit they may be tearmed <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> and <hi>Canonicall,</hi> for the edification of the faithfull, for which end they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into the Canon of the <hi>Bible.</hi> With
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4329:36"/> this <hi>Distinction,</hi> that which is ſpoken by Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> and written by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall Councell of <hi>Carthage must bee vnderstood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Pag. 170.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon you ſo much relie, no doubt will now ſtand you in great ſtead. <hi>Caietan</hi> taketh away your obiection with this diſtinction. Beſides, by your leaue, it may ſeeme, theſe books were not ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by that <hi>Councell.</hi> For how then could <note n="a" place="margin">19. <hi>Mor.</hi> 13.</note> S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> long after haue doubted of theſe bookes, calling them <hi>Libros non Canonicos, Books that were not Canonicall?</hi> Your owne <note n="b" place="margin">Locis Theol. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> §. Ad quartum.</note> 
                  <hi>Canus</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that if they had been ſo ratified, it had been neither for <hi>Gregorie,</hi> nor any other to haue afterward made any doubt of them. Why ſhould you then ſtile it an <note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 169.</note> 
                  <hi>Artificiall Colluſion,</hi> if our <hi>D.</hi> ſay that S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſeemeth to ſignifie, that there is no place of <hi>Scripture for prayer for the dead,</hi> when beſides the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Church,</hi> hee alledgeth only that one out of the <hi>Machabees,</hi> which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:4329:37"/> bookes are not properly <hi>Canonicall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You take all things, I ſee, with the left hand; you would faine find a mote in <hi>D. H.</hi> his eie, and yet you will not ſee the beame in your owne illatiue. <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Higgons.</hi> pag. 170.</note> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> you ſay, makes mention of the old <hi>Scripture, Ergo,</hi> he intimateth that in the <hi>new Testament,</hi> ſome reliefe for the dead, is either plainly expreſſed, or ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently deduced from thence. In ſadnes I ſhould be glad to ſee a <hi>Logique</hi> of your making: you haue ſuch paſſing skill to conclude, <hi>Quid libet ex Quolibet.</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustines</hi> words are theſe, <note n="e" place="margin">De cura pro mort. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If this were read no where in the old Scripture, yet there is no ſmall authoritie of the vniuerſall Church,</hi> &amp;c. He maketh a negatiue ſuppoſition of the old teſtament, from whence you infer an affirmatiue poſition, that there is proofe in the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <note n="f" place="margin">Fallacia ab inſufficiente diuiſione.</note> A good Conſequent: all one, as if a man ſhould ſay, <hi>M. Theomiſus is not in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard:</hi> Ergo, <hi>he is in the Church.</hi> Had there been any ſuch place there to be found, S. <hi>Augustine</hi> was not ſuch a ſtranger vnto
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4329:37"/> it, but that hee could haue produced it <note n="g" place="margin">Doctus ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba proſert de theſauro ſuo noua &amp; vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</note> with a wet finger. Neither was he <hi>tàm imperitus rerum aestimator,</hi> as to thinke that the cuſtome of the Church would paſſe more currant, then that protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vnto which the Lord hath ſet his hand and ſeale. Wherfore wi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h far more probabilitie, might you haue argued thus; S. <hi>Augustine</hi> mentioneth only the <hi>old,</hi> which is not vndoubtedly Scripture: <hi>Ergo,</hi> hee did not find any Canonicall Scripture to confirme it. Yea, but <hi>Plus vident oculi quàm oculus:</hi> happily your <hi>Jeſuiticall ſocietie</hi> (as hauing the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a later, more learned, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced age) hath digged ſo far into that ſacred mine, that they haue now found the <hi>Gemme,</hi> which S. <hi>Augustines</hi> age ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaw. And why not? Were there no more ſimples then <hi>Galen</hi> diſcouered, we ſhould haue but ſimple Phyſitians. Time hath bred more maturitie in all Arts, which did but bloſſome in the former age: and well might it be as heauie an imputation to our vnthriftie daies, as it
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4329:38"/> was to that ſeruant, who returned his Talent without increaſe, if wee ſhould purchaſe no more then our fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed vs. Well, if you haue it, what need you be ſo daintie, to keepe it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der locke and key from the view of the world? If this proofe out of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament were once knowne, it would make your Purgatory-boxe richer by many thouſands. I know no man ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectleſſe of himſelfe, but would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie part with one moytie of his meanes, for his future reliefe. <note n="h" place="margin">Empti estis pretio.</note> But vntill you bring Scripture affirmatiuelie to proue it, you muſt giue <hi>D. Hum.</hi> leaue, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie in the anſwerers place) to <hi>pretend,</hi> nay to plead <note n="i" place="margin">Jn lege quid ſcriptum est? quomodo legis? <hi>Luk. 10.26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scripture</hi> negatiuely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, your former ground being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlie anſwered.</p>
               <p>It were well, you would ſay, if wee could plead ſo to the authoritie of our Church, <note n="k" place="margin">Pag. 170.</note> 
                  <hi>Her Soueraigntie is impeacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, without any other proof forceable, from whence it is not only inſolencie, but madneſſe to decline. Pulchrè dictum:</hi> This is your
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4329:38"/> Ladies firſt <hi>A. B. C.</hi> The Church is as much beholding to you, for maintaining her right, as S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> 
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>for your ſecret and peculiar affection.</hi> Nay, as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was to his ſcholars, inſteed of <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> you will haue <hi>ipſa dixit.</hi> Me thinks I ſee you playing <hi>Demetrius,</hi> your craft is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to decay, and therfore you are faine to crie, <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 19.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Magna Diana Epheſiorum,</hi> or (which is in effect as much) <hi>Magna Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia Romanorum.</hi> For when you ſpeake of the Church, I take it, you haue reference to your former <note n="n" place="margin">Pag. 14.</note> aſſertion, <hi>That your Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church is of more powerfull principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then the reſt.</hi> Indeed had the <hi>Scriptures, Creeds,</hi> and <hi>foure first generall Councels</hi> been deriued from thence, it might haue been more tolerablie auerred: But wee ſhould do the <hi>Greek Church</hi> much wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, to decke your <hi>Romiſh,</hi> with her Plumes, hauing receiued no <hi>foundation of faith</hi> from you at all. Of the true Church, who is he that ſaith not with S. <hi>Augustine, Non parua eccleſiae auctoritas?</hi> Well doth her <hi>Modestie,</hi> well doth her <hi>Fidelitie</hi> deſerue
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4329:39"/> honorable eſteeme. Shee taketh not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her to controule the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> her mother, from whom ſhee drew her firſt breath: ſhe openeth not her mouth, til her mother haue deliuered her mind; ſhe commeth not of her owne head with any ſleeueleſſe arrend: No other meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage doth ſhe bring, to the ſeruants of the Lords houſe, then that which her mother hath giuen her in charge. But of the place of her former reſidence, and how many painted Antichriſtian <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots,</hi> haue ietted vp and downe in her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and vſurped her <note n="o" place="margin">Apocal. 17.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Chaire of State;</hi> it would aske a long treatiſe to declare. And indeed my patience can hardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, that our dead <hi>Doctor</hi> ſhould lie ſo long at the mercie of your mercileſſe pen. As I haue disburthened him of the impoſed <hi>Colluſion,</hi> ſo will I now beſtow a few lines to ſhroud him from the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 171.</note> 
                  <hi>Deluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Deluſion</hi> with which he is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is <hi>ambiguitie of ſpeech:</hi> for <note n="b" place="margin">Pag. 171.</note> whereas the <hi>commendation,</hi> whereof S. <hi>Augustine</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:4329:39"/> ſpeaketh, is referred to the ſoules of the <hi>Dead, D. Humfrey,</hi> in his <hi>Rhetoricall flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,</hi> doth pretend, that we in our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges retaine the ancient <hi>commendation</hi> of the <hi>Dead;</hi> by which he would make the credulous Reader belieue, that Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> himſelfe doth <hi>conuell</hi> the vſe of <hi>prayer</hi> for the dead, maintaining it no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, then we now do. <note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 172.</note> The <hi>Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Reader?</hi> Nay he were a ſottiſh Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that ſhould gather any ſuch beliefe out of <hi>D. Humfreies</hi> words, who hath not any one ſentence to that purpoſe. Where doth he deny that S. <hi>Augustine</hi> did not allow praier for the <hi>Dead?</hi> this had been a <hi>Deluſion,</hi> a notable <hi>Figment,</hi> an eminent <hi>Deprauation;</hi> nay he plainlie confeſſeth it, citing S. <hi>Aug.</hi> owne words, <hi>That this commendation of the dead, is an ancient custome of the Church,</hi> in that place which you haue formerly mentioned. And yet by the way it is not amiſſe, to put you in mind, what S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where doth confeſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> many to haue erred in their deuotion towards the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:4329:40"/> dead <note n="*" place="margin">August. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid. ad Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. cap. <hi>67.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ex humana beneuolentia:</hi> and ſo wee find alſo that the entire loue of his mother <hi>Monica,</hi> and other his deare friends made him ſomwhat too forward in this point. And why may not this be one of thoſe things of which hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>ad Januarium?</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Aug. ad Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarium.</note> 
                  <hi>Multa huiuſmodi, propter nonnullarum vel ſanctarum vel tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulentarum perſonarum ſcandala deuitanda, liberiùs improbare non audeo.</hi> There are many things, which, becauſe I would not offend, the conſciences of thoſe that are otherwiſe well minded, nor prooue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are turbulentlie affected, I dare not reproue as I would. Not to diuert you with theſe oppoſitions, that which our doctor concludes out of S. <hi>Aug.</hi> is, <hi>that he hath no Scripture for prayer for the dead.</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Cont. Camp. pag. <hi>262.</hi> pars <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oportere nos orare pro mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſi Scripturae praecepta reſpiciamus,</hi> which is as much he asketh. Nay hee alleageth S. <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> owne words, <hi>Veteremeſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem:</hi> that the <hi>commendation</hi> of the dead is ratified by <hi>cuſtome.</hi> Now becauſe <hi>commendation</hi> of the <hi>dead</hi> ſignifieth both
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4329:40"/> the prayer of <hi>ſupplication</hi> (as you <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſlie</hi> abuſe it) and of <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> (as it is now in our colleges for the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of the founders <hi>reſpectiuely</hi> vſed) <hi>D. Hum.</hi> aſſuming this part ſaith, <hi>VVe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the commendation,</hi> &amp;c. and doth not therefore abſolutely denie the other, that S. <hi>Auguſtins Humana beneuolentia</hi> was ſomewhat inclined to that part. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee I any reaſon, why hee ſhould ſtriue to make the world beleeue that S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth <note n="f" place="margin">Pag. 172.</note> 
                  <hi>conuel the vſe of prayer" for the dead,</hi> as if our faith were to bee" pinned vpon S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſleeue.</p>
               <p>And yet let mee tell you this, for ought that euer I could reade, there is no ſuch great difference, betweene our <hi>practiſe,</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtines cuſtome,</hi> as you ſurmiſe. For beſides the pious cuſtome of our Colleges, which celebrate the memorie of the dead, with commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their liberalitie, beſides their Chriſtian buriall, and the dole beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the poore, (which are rather <hi>ſolatia <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuorum quam ſubſidia mortuor.</hi>) we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:4329:41"/> pray euen in our Churches, for the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full departed, <hi>that God would hasten their ioyfull</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Apocal. 23.20.</note> 
                  <hi>reſurrection,</hi> and the full accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of their happineſſe, both for the bodie and the ſoule, by which they are not a little relieued. This is as much as the Scripture will warrant: and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, bare cuſtome backed onely with that place of the <hi>Machabees</hi> muſt not lead vs.</p>
               <p>This is that which <hi>D. Humfrey</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deluſion profeſſeth, when hee ſaith, <note n="h" place="margin">Cont. Camp. pars <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>262.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quae haec ſtupida impietas, vt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes defuncti à viuentium meritis, à mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorum cucullis &amp; ocreis, à ſacerdotum miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis &amp; precibus, ab amicorum teiunijs alijſque operibus dependeant?</hi> What blockiſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie is it, that men departed ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon the merits of thoſe that are aliue, vpon the cowles and buskins of Monkes, vpon the Maſſes and praiers of the Prieſts, vpon the faſts, Dirges, and ſuch like workes of their friends? What <hi>Deluſion</hi> can there be in ſo plaine words? <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (ſaith he) pleades cuſtome, but
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:4329:41"/> he implieth that there is no Scripture to maintaine this oblation. So that, that which he looked for from his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries was this, not that they ſhould <note n="i" place="margin">Pag. 38.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the difference between our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and theirs, but that they ſhould produce <hi>Scripture,</hi> to iuſtifie their <hi>Altar,</hi> their holy <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> their ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>intention,</hi> wherin they diſſent from vs: and wherein S. <hi>Augustine</hi> bids them truſt to their owne proofe, as hauing no other ſhelter, but <hi>Custome</hi> for them at all.</p>
               <p>How can you recompence this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Saint, for thoſe many cauils, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you haue ſought to blaſt his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, blazing indeed your own ſhame? I hope you will now giue him leaue to borrow the ſaying of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Galath. 6.17.</note> 
                  <hi>De caetero nemo ſit mihi molestus:</hi> he now reſteth in peace, hauing left behind him, not only the happie memorie of a bleſſed life, but alſo ſo many obliged friends, who will neuer ſuffer any of his elaborate lines to be blurred with wrongfull diſgrace,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:4329:42"/> eſpecially by thoſe, who with a <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi> of great names, with <hi>Ponderations,</hi> and <hi>Conſiderations</hi> thinke to beard the truth. <note n="l" place="margin">1. Eſd. 4.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Magna est veritas &amp; praeualet.</hi> It is not one ſtrained Scripture that can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the declining waight of decayed Purgatorie; it will aske more reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then the book of God will willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beſtow vpon it. <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> you ſay, is the iſſue vnto which your thoughts do finallie incline, and therefore hauing alreadie laid flat your weaker defences, I will plant my batterie to your ſtrongeſt <hi>Bulwarke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd for as much as M. <hi>Caluins</hi> cenſure of <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> is held by you as <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 53.</note> 
                  <hi>a ſpecious venditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> though I will giue you leaue to make your beſt of his <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> which whilome was your adored <hi>Saint,</hi> yet will I (maugre your colourable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations) make good the truth of this his aſſertion. That <hi>Purgatory is a pernicious
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:4329:42"/> fiction of Satan: diſgracefull vnto the great mercy of God: euacuating the croſſe of Chriſt: diſſipating and peruerting our faith.</hi> You think to blow him vp with a <note n="b" place="margin">Pag. 131.</note> 
                  <hi>Syllogiſme:</hi> Now then haue at your <note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 154.</note> 
                  <hi>Point-deuice.</hi> Purgatory is a <hi>Satanical</hi> figment: I proue it thus: <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
                  <hi>That place which neither God made;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi> 
                  <hi>nor Christ mentioned;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 
                  <hi>nor the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles beleeued;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi> 
                  <hi>nor the Primitiue Church embraced;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi> 
                  <hi>nor the firſt foure general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels confirmed; is a meere figment of Satan: But ſuch a place is purgatorie:</hi> Ergo, <hi>A meere figment of Satan.</hi> For the firſt, <hi>God made nothing in vaine nor ſuperfluous: But Purgatorie is vaine and ſuperfluous:</hi> Ergo. My <hi>Minor</hi> is proued thus: <hi>VVhatſoeuer is in the Lords field, is either</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 13.8. and 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Corne or Tares; But Purgatorie ſerueth for neither of theſe:</hi> (there being a Barne prouided for the one, and an vnquenchable fire for the other) Ergo, <note n="e" place="margin">Maior vis in negatione, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in affirmatione.</note> 
                  <hi>There being no third ſort of Perſons, this third imaginarie place is ſuperfluous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond, <hi>Had Christ deliuered a Doctrine ſo materiall, it would haue been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:4329:43"/>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Accepi à D<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino. <hi>1. Cor. 11.23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>recorded: But there is no ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, either registred by the Euangelists, or alledged by your ſelues.</hi> Ergo, <hi>neuer men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the third: <hi>Had the Apostles belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, they had been iniurious to the distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoules, to haue continued their paines by their vncharitable Concealement, especially giuing written instructions of</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Praeceptum domini non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, conſilium autem do. <hi>1. Cor. 7.25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>leſſe mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: But in all their aduertiſements, touching thoſe that ſleepe, it is ſuppreſſed:</hi> Ergo, <hi>not beleeued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the fourth: <hi>Jf Purgatorie were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the Primitiue Church, then was it, as an Apostolicall Tradition:</hi> (there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no expreſſe Scripture to ratifie it,) <hi>But not as an Apostolicall tradition:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Not at all embraced.</hi> That it was not held by them as an Apoſtolicall Tradition, I proue thus: <hi>As it was held by the Primitiue Church, ſo was it deriued to posteritie: But it was not deriued to posteritie, as an Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall tradition:</hi> Ergo, <hi>not ſo embraced by the Primitiue Church.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> I proue thus: <hi>Euery Apostolicall tradition is knowne
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:4329:43"/> by theſe two</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Aug. cont. Donat. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>markes;</hi> Firſt it muſt be held <hi>ab vniuerſa Eccleſia,</hi> there is the <hi>Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> Secondly, <hi>Semper,</hi> there is the <hi>Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie: But neither had Purgatorie generall approbation, nor perpetuall ſucceſſion:</hi> Ergo, <hi>no Apostolicall tradition.</hi> The Minor is confirmed by the teſtimony of <hi>Polydore,</hi> 
                  <note n="i" place="margin">De inuent. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aliquandiu incognitum fuit, &amp; ſerò cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vniuerſae eccleſiae.</hi> It was a great while before <hi>Purgatorie</hi> was heard of, and but of late knowne to the vniuerſal Church. <hi>Serò</hi> cutteth off the <hi>Perpetuitie,</hi> and the emphaſis of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſae,</hi> intimateth no <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſucceſſiuely it was deriued from the <hi>Primitiue Church,</hi> then vndoubtedlie it could be no ſtranger to the <hi>Greeke Church:</hi> But, to put you out of all hope of this, your <note n="k" place="margin">Articulo <hi>18.</hi> cont. Luth.</note> 
                  <hi>Roffenſis</hi> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to bring you this heauie newes: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad hunc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em Graecis non est cognitum Purgatorium:</hi> The <hi>Greekes</hi> know not <hi>Purgatorie</hi> vnto this day Nay he further explaineth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, propounding this challenge, <hi>Legat qui velit Grecorum veterum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarios, &amp;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:4329:44"/> nullum, quantum opinor, aut quam rariſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum de Purgatorio ſermonem inueniet:</hi> Reade he that liſt the ancient Greeke Commentaries, &amp; he ſhal find either lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or no mention at all of <hi>Purgatorie.</hi> Where is now your continued <hi>Perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</hi> He ſerueth your <hi>Generalitie</hi> with the ſame ſauce: <hi>Sed neque Latini ſimul omnes, at ſenſim huius rei veritatem conceperunt:</hi> Neither did all of the <hi>Latine</hi> Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it at once, (there was ſome ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> wombe) and by degrees they receiued this truth. So that it was long before they receiued it, <hi>Ergo,</hi> no <hi>Perpetuitie:</hi> they receiued it not all at once; (there was belike ſome oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>Ergo</hi> no <hi>Generalitie:</hi> and then the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter muſt yeeld vnto the former, by your owne <note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> rule.</p>
               <p>Now for the fifth and laſt member of my propoſition, <hi>If it were confirmed by the first foure generall Councels, or any of them, then it will appeare by their Canons: But</hi> 
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Jnsta.</note> 
                  <hi>no one Canon can be thence produced: Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go not all confirmed.</hi> And ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:4329:44"/> mere <hi>Satanicall</hi> figment. Thus doth your <note n="n" place="margin">Page 39.</note> 
                  <hi>Dagon</hi> fal downe before the <hi>Arke.</hi> Had it not been for your grand Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, S. <hi>Homer,</hi> S. <hi>Plato,</hi> and S. <hi>Virgil,</hi> you would neuer haue knowne how to haue ſet your compaſſe, for the diſcouerie of this new found world. And yet, if a man ſhould aske the beſt nauigator of you all, in what degree, &amp; how many leagues <hi>Purgatorie</hi> is from the <hi>Jnfernall Cape,</hi> I thinke he would be put to his trumpes. Only <hi>Beda</hi> his <hi>ghoſt</hi> commeth ſomewhat neere the marke in his <hi>Carde</hi> (which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>Purgatorie</hi> vnder the earth in the ſuburbs of <hi>Hell</hi>) by which whoſoeuer is led, may happily make but a ſorrie voiage. Neither ſee I any reaſon, why you ſhould not as well beleeue <hi>Alcui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who peremtorilie maintaineth, that it is ſituate in the <note n="o" place="margin">Somnium Scipioner.</note> aire. But if one bee ſent vnto you from the <note n="p" place="margin">As true as S. Bernards miracle. pag. 71.</note> 
                  <hi>dead,</hi> (wherein you are more happy then <hi>Diues</hi> his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,) I cannot much blame you, if you heare him. Well, <hi>Quod vbique eſt, nullibi eſt,</hi> it is in ſo many places, that indeed it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:4329:45"/> is in no place. But it proceedeth from a iuſt iudgement of God, that ſuch <note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 11.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians</hi> ſhould haue their language di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided: the world is now growne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of ſuch <hi>Alcumists,</hi> who haue exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted our treaſures with long expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> which yet could neuer be found.</p>
               <p>The next point, wherein I am to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, is, <hi>that it diſgraceth the mercie of God, euacuateth the croſſe of Chriſt, and (conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie) peruerteth our faith.</hi> The truth whereof is ſo euidently apparant, that I ſhall not make any long demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth vs an infallible rule, how to order our opinions in this caſe; <note n="r" place="margin">Cont. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. lib. <hi>20.</hi> ca. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Secundùm libros certos prophetarum &amp; Apoſtolorum, de caeteris libris, vel fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vel infidelium liberè iudicemus:</hi> wee may freelie iudge of all other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and conſequently of al traditions, according to their agreements, or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements, with the certaine <hi>Propheticall</hi> and <hi>Apostolicall</hi> writ. So that if I can now prooue that <hi>Purgatorie</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:4329:45"/> reſpects, is repugnant to the written word, I ſhall alſo with one &amp; the ſame labor, proue it no Apoſtolicall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, vpon which you wholly <note n="ſ" place="margin">Page 11.</note> relie. There is no one point, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more vrgeth, then that the Lord will haue no partner to rob him of his glorie; <note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 4.11. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Tibi honor &amp; gloria,</hi> ſay the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. This glorie, as it did ſhine in the creation of man, ſo is the luſtre thereof as bright in his redemption. As we lay no claime to haue been any helper in the creation, ſo can wee not part ſtakes in our redemption. <note n="b" place="margin">1. Iohn 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>The blood of Chriſt purgeth vs from all ſinnes:</hi> if ſinnes be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, then the <hi>puniſhment</hi> is remitted: the cauſe being taken away, the effect cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: if from <hi>all</hi> ſinnes, then as well <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> as <hi>veniall,</hi> as you terme them. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Lord ſay, He that is ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie yeeres in <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> but <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 10.9.</note> 
                  <hi>he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth</hi> ſhall bee ſaued. My argument the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtandeth thus: The <hi>ſoules in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, are either puniſhed for thoſe ſinnes, which Chriſts blood hath wholly purged; or for thoſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:4329:46"/> which he hath not whollie purged:</hi> if for thoſe which Chriſt hath wholly purged, then muſt there needs be <hi>iniuſtice in God to impriſon them whoſe debts are fully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged:</hi> if for ſinnes that hee hath not wholly purged, then it followeth, either that he is not <note n="d" place="margin">Iohn 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>the lamb of God, that taketh away the ſinnes of the world,</hi> leauing ſome part behind, or that the workes of God, nay his mercy, <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 144.9.</note> 
                  <hi>which paſſeth al his works,</hi> is imperfect: or that mans ſatiſfaction muſt goe hand in hand with Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by making that good which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his paſſion; with which ſurmiſe the Lord will not ſuffer his glorie to be ecclipſed.</p>
               <p>And ſurelie if <hi>Apelles</hi> leaue his picture vnperfect, it is in vaine for any other of his craft to take it in hand; Neither can I vnderſtand, why the blood of Chriſt, apprehended by faith in this life, ſhould be of leſſe force, then when it is applied by <hi>Baals</hi> prieſt, when we are dead, to free vs from that <hi>doome.</hi> Your owne wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are not aſhamed to ſay, that a <note n="f" place="margin">Reuelat. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittae. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Biſhop
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:4329:46"/> of Rome</hi> his prayers did deliuer <hi>Traian</hi> a Heathen Emperour from hell, who had been dead many hundred of yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and yet you thinke much, nay you ſay that we inſiſt in the ſteps of the <note n="g" place="margin">Pag. 53.</note> 
                  <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatians, Neſtorians,</hi> and the like, when we profeſſe that the <note n="h" place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>handwriting,</hi> which was againſt vs, being faſtened to the croſſe of Chriſt, and the bond being cancelled, we are no longer liable to the penaltie thereof; albeit the Scripture ſaith, that <note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note> 
                  <hi>he appeared once to put away ſin:</hi> how? by meriting, that the penall ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of <hi>Purgatorie</hi> might make vs cleane? No ſuch matter, but by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe, <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt hath purged our ſinnes,</hi> not by vs, as making vs our owne Sauiors, but by himſelfe. <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura, quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi> If the Leproſie of<note n="l" place="margin">4. King. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Naaman</hi> be clenſed by the water of <hi>Iordan,</hi> what ſtandeth hee in need of <hi>Abanah,</hi> or <hi>Pharphar?</hi> Chriſt was offered for the ſinnes of many, and yet, as if he had but taken a longer day
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:4329:47"/> of paiment, the <hi>vnbloodie ſacrifice</hi> muſt be dailie renewed; as if the ſheading of his pretious blood vpon the croſſe, were leſſe effectuall then your <hi>breaden idoll</hi> in a ſhauelings hand, whom blind <hi>ſupersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> holdeth to be able to rid them from that dolefull place; wherein, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that <hi>one</hi> 
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 7.27.</note> 
                  <hi>oblation</hi> of himſelfe once offered, they are for further <hi>purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to bee enthralled. If the Lord hath aſſigned them that place, how can your <hi>Romiſh</hi> indulgences ſet them at libertie? where is your commiſſion? if you will looſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all, it muſt be while they are on the earth: it is appointed to all men, <note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>That they must die,</hi> and after death commeth iudgement: <note n="o" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Mortui nihil no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt amplius, nec habent vltra mercedem:</hi> The dead know nothing at all: As the <note n="p" place="margin">Jbid. cap. <hi>11.3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tree falleth, ſo must it lie:</hi> 
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Cyprian. de mortal.</note> 
                  <hi>Qualem te in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit Deus cùm de hoc mundo euocat, talem te iudicat:</hi> As God findeth thee at thy death, ſo will he iudge thee. If the Lord haue aſſigned no ſuch place to them, as is plaine by the premiſſes, then are you
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:4329:47"/> cruell comforters, who for your owne gaine do terrifie the departing ſoule of him, whom Chriſt hath dearely bought, with ſuch ſpectricall deluſions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe that are carnallie minded, to truſt to that <hi>after-reliefe,</hi> which they ſhall neuer find. If this be not, I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what is, a <hi>Doctrine of diuels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribeth faith to be <note n="r" place="margin">Hebr. 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſperandarum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ground of things that are to bee hoped for from <hi>Christ:</hi> but you will haue it thus, <hi>Fides eſt rerum ferendarum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, making it the ground of thoſe things that are to bee ſuffered by our ſelues. For without your <hi>Purgatorie</hi> paines, you take little hold of any hope of future ioy. No men talke more of the Croſſe of Chriſt then you, none derogate from it ſo much as you, by ioyning your own pains as a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his ſufferings. S. <hi>Paul</hi> thought it enough to <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>know Christ, and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied:</hi> but he is a dullard in your ſchoole, that knoweth not <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> and how he muſt be there purged. Is this any better
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:4329:48"/> then to leſſen the meaſureleſſe mercie of God, to pare the croſſe of Chriſt, and alter the nature of faith? As if the Lords ſommer-liuerie of <hi>euerlasting life</hi> were giuen vs onlie in the broad-cloth, in the generall merit of Chriſt, with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſo, that vnleſſe we plaie the Tailors our ſelues, &amp; make it vp by our owne purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it muſt neuer come on our backs. Whereas hee giueth it vnto vs, readie made with his owne hands: for as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> 
                  <hi>The gift of God is eternall life.</hi> How do you then ſay, that we muſt be firſt infernallie purged? What, <note n="u" place="margin">Matth. 16.18.</note> ſhall not the gates of <hi>Hell</hi> preuaile againſt vs, and ſhall the muddie wall of Purgatorie hedge vs in? Hath his <note n="x" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſoule</hi> gone downe to the nethermoſt hell, and yet made no paſſage thorow the ſuburbs of hel? Hath he bound the <note n="y" place="margin">Matt. 12.29</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrong man,</hi> that he ſhould not harme vs, and will he now torment vs himſelfe, or ſet we know not whom to do it?</p>
               <p>Let vs argue the caſe a little more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie. You all grant with one conſent,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:4329:48"/> that the ſoules of thoſe, that are in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, are ſuch as haue died in the faith, howſoeuer otherwiſe tainted with ſinne: Now they that died in the faith, died in the Lord: They that died in the Lord, reſt from their <note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Labours:</hi> They that reſt from their labours, are ſo far from being worſe, that they are in much better plight then they were. <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 6.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that beleeueth</hi> in him that ſent mee, (ſaith our Sauiour) doth paſſe from death, (not to <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> but) to <hi>life.</hi> Againe, they that die in the faith, haue <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>peace towards God;</hi> They that haue peace towards God, are iuſtified by <hi>Christ;</hi> They that are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Christ are free from the Law, and being free from the Law, <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Quis accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit?</hi> Who ſhall lay any thing to their charge? Yea but they haue ſome droſſe to be purged. Indeed S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Haec fuistis:</hi> but he addeth, <hi>ſed abluti estis,</hi> &amp;c. But you are waſhed, but you are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but you are iuſtified in the name of our Lord Ieſus, and by the Spirit of our God. And being ſo, the Wiſe mans ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:4329:49"/> muſt be applied,<note n="f" place="margin">Wiſd. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtorum animae in manu Dei ſunt:</hi> The ſoules of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous are in the hand of God. What tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can then touch them?</p>
               <p>Hath not the Lord heere the fire of afflictions, to melt our hearts, and caſt them into a new mould? Hath hee not heere the fire of his Spirit, to purge our conſciences from dead workes? If theſe will do no good, what purification can we expect from your temporall fire of Purgatorie? Without doubt, ſaid <note n="g" place="margin">Jn Leuit. lib. <hi>9.</hi> apud Cyril.</note> 
                  <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> we ſhal feele the vnquenchable fire, vnleſſe we now intreat the Lord to ſend downe from heauen a Purgatorie fire, whereby worldlie deſires may be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſumed in our minds. They which are dead (ſaith <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> in Eſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyril</hi>) can adde nothing to the things which they haue done, but ſhall remaine as they were left, and wait for the time of the laſt iudgement. The reaſon is aſſigned by the Spirit, <note n="i" place="margin">Apoc. 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Opera eorum ſequuntur eos:</hi> Their workes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, euen at the heeles. Why would you then haue vs now liue in greater
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:4329:49"/> darknes, then they which liued vnder the <hi>Leuiticall</hi> law? Who, albeit they offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſundrie ſacrifices, for ſundrie ſorts of perſons, and different ſins, yet reade wee not, that euer they offered any for the dead. So that this doctrine of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie cannot more trulie be fathered vpon any, then ſuch <hi>Pagans,</hi> who being conuerted to the faith, were of opinion, <note n="k" place="margin">Can. pars <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>103.</hi> a.</note> that Chriſtian religion ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate any thing from their wonted kindnes to their deceaſed friends.</p>
               <p>But alas what boone can wee expect from ſuch ſacrifices? <note n="l" place="margin">Chryſost. de Lazaro.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui in praeſenti vita peccata non abluit, postea nullam conſolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem inueniet.</hi> Our ſinnes muſt bee heere purged, elſe ſhal not our ſoules be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after comforted.<note n="m" place="margin">Cyprian. cont. Demet.</note> 
                  <hi>Quando istinc exceſſum fuerit, nullus iam poenitentiae locus, nullus ſatisfactionis effectus; hîc vita aut amittitur aut tenetur.</hi> When we are once hence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, there is no place left for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, no roome for ſatisfaction; ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is won or loſt while wee are heere. Were there any one precept, practiſe or
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:4329:50"/> promiſe in the Scripture (which <hi>Petrus à Soto</hi> vtterly denieth) to giue but ſome ſhadow of allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſuch Paganiſme, your defence were far more colourable. Beſides, if I bee not deceiued, it were worth the while to debate, what ſhall be done with thoſe of the middle ranke of offenders, who ſhall ſuruiue at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt; when Purgatorie ſhal be cleane extinct. If you ſay, they ſhall bee ſaued without further purgation, then either there muſt bee <hi>partialitie</hi> in the Iudge, to afford them more fauour, then thoſe who daily depart this life; or elſe you muſt grant, that there is no ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of Purgatorie, as you pretend: if you ſay they ſhall bee damned, then doe you taxe the Lord of <hi>vniustice,</hi> in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that meanes of Purgation to them, which he hath alwaies afforded to thoſe that were of their ranke. Thus doth one abſurditie draw on another.</p>
               <p>I haue been ſomewhat the more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious in this point of Purgatorie, for as much as I wel perceiue, it is the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:4329:50"/> of moſt of your <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> 
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lema malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All theſe I am prepared to proue vſed, practiſed and iuſtified by the Antichriſtian Biſhops of Rome.</p>
                  </note> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> your <hi>merits,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi> 
                  <hi>ſatisfactions,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 
                  <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi> 
                  <hi>ſupererogations,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi> 
                  <hi>Maſſes,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi> 
                  <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi> 
                  <hi>ſuperaltaries,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi> 
                  <hi>noone-day lampes,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi> 
                  <hi>Dirges,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi> 
                  <hi>Christning</hi> and <hi>buriall tapers,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi> 
                  <hi>oblations,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi> 
                  <hi>Roods,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi> 
                  <hi>Jmages,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">14</hi> 
                  <hi>croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creepings,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">15</hi> 
                  <hi>Beads,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">16</hi> 
                  <hi>Crucifixes,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">17</hi> 
                  <hi>pictures,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">18</hi> 
                  <hi>graines,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">19</hi> 
                  <hi>Jncenſe,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">20</hi> 
                  <hi>hallowed Cemete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">21</hi> 
                  <hi>Holy water,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">22</hi> 
                  <hi>oyle,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">23</hi> 
                  <hi>ſalt,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">24</hi> 
                  <hi>ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">25</hi> 
                  <hi>Couents,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">26</hi> 
                  <hi>Proceſſions,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">27</hi> 
                  <hi>Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">28</hi> 
                  <hi>Reliques,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">29</hi> 
                  <hi>Stewiſh Pardons,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">30</hi> 
                  <hi>Jndulgences,</hi> and ſuch rifraffe, iugling traſh, and Babies ſports, haue not onlie mutuall reference, but fundamental de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance vpon this. Which being thus ſhaken, will, I hope, no longer <note n="o" place="margin">Si caecus cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ducat, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo in foueam. <hi>Luk. 6.39.</hi>
                  </note> ſupport and patronage the reſt. But why ſhould I hope to ſatisfie you in this? as if I could vrge that, which hath not been long ſince propounded to this purpoſe. What is it that can gaine aſſent in thoſe, who are wilfully peruerſe?</p>
               <p>To giue you one inſtance for all, how often hath it been demonſtratiuely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that ſetting ſome friuolous Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:4329:51"/> aſide, our Countrie of <hi>Britanie</hi> was no whit beholding to proud and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent<note n="p" place="margin">Beda. Ec. hist. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> your great <hi>Gregories</hi> delegat, for any matter of faith? <note n="q" place="margin">Anno <hi>580.</hi> Polyd. praefat. ad Ton ſtal. praefixa Gildae. Aug. <hi>came in</hi> Anno <hi>597.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gildas</hi> his teſtimonie hath been vrged, (who liued before <hi>Augustines</hi> comming) that the <hi>Britons</hi> receiued the Chriſtian faith fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning: <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>An</hi> 58. <hi>n</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> hath told you, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was here: <note n="ſ" place="margin">De curand. Graec. affect. <hi>l. 9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Theodoret,</hi> that S. <hi>Paul:</hi> 
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 40.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> that <hi>Simon Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotes:</hi> and ſome, <note n="u" place="margin">Baron. an. <hi>39.</hi> n. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Joſeph de Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea</hi> did plant the faith amongſt vs. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie forceable inducements haue been produced, that euen in the Primitiue Church, Chriſtianitie harbored in this Iſle. Theſe inſtances, and many more, haue been againe and againe renewed, without any verified contradiction: and yet, as if it had been a matter which you neuer heard of afore, you would (as in all your other points,) make vs in this follow you vp and downe, wearying the world with a circular diſcuſſe, bobbing your credulous Ladies with theſe <hi>Syre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> inſinuations. As long as you are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:4329:51"/> thus partially minded, arguments will bee no inducements: the world will bee ſooner ended then this matter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided: your <hi>Romiſh</hi> practiſe being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but to guild old weather-beaten obiections with new gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring words. Let vs bring neuer ſo manie writs of errour, you will ſtill reduce your ſelfe to your old plaint. From a new Conuert, I expected new proofes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you may know from what affection theſe my former lines haue iſſued, I haue reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued yet one corner of my let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a more friendlie conference, whereby you ſhall perceiue, that as you are <hi>Romiſh,</hi> I haue bent thoſe forces that were next at hand to ſupplant your error: as you are my <hi>Countriman,</hi> in whom I reſolue there is ſome hope, my beſt meanes ſhall not bee wanting for your behoofe. Let me then ſay to <hi>M.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:4329:52"/> Theophilus Hyggons,</hi> as he that ſat in the midſt of the ſeauen golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Candleſticks, ſaid vnto the Angell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member from whence thou art fallen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and doe the firſt workes.</hi> The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie wherein you were borne, is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturallie to be deſpiſed: the friends, by whom you were bred, are not vnkindlie to bee contemned: neither is the faith, whereinto you were baptiſed, if you rightlie iudge, ſo inconſideratelie to be forſaken. <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 44.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The Kings daughter is all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within;</hi> howſoeuer the Babylonian harlot may bee more gaudie without. Why ſhould you thinke our written word of leſſe value, then your headge-creeping traditions? why ſhould Chriſts merits be leſſened by your owne ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions? why ſhould the debt be again exacted, which <hi>Christs</hi> blood hath once for al fully paid? Had we <hi rend="sup">1</hi> an idolatrous, heatheniſh, or ſuperſtitious religion; were we <hi rend="sup">2</hi> worſhippers of images; <hi rend="sup">3</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of holie marriage; <hi rend="sup">4</hi> rebelliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie affected to the higher powers; <hi rend="sup">5</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealers
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:4329:52"/> of the word, impriſoning it in an vnknowne tongue; <hi rend="sup">6</hi> maintainers of ſtewes; <hi rend="sup">7</hi> did wee keepe backe the cup from the Laitie, which the Lord hath allotted them; <hi rend="sup">8</hi> did wee hearten men in their ſinnes, by granting future indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences; or <hi rend="sup">9</hi> by putting them in hope, to haue that done for them by others after they are dead, which they haue not done for themſelues whileſt they were aliue; if wee ſought to ſeduce poore ſoules by lying <hi rend="sup">10</hi> Legends, and deceiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi rend="sup">11</hi> wonders: then might you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt that we belong to the kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſo leaue vs, hauing an <note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Exite</hi> vnder the Lords ſeale. But if wee preach <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> and him crucified, if our faith be wholly directed to his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, our hope to his mercies, our charity to his deputies, the Saints vpon earth, if we maintaine that word, and retaine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thoſe Sacraments, which Chriſts holie inſtitution hath warranted, then, <hi>Quis vos faſcinauit?</hi> O ye branſicke and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh fugitiues, who hath bewitched you,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:4329:53"/> that you ſhould not obey the truth? Are you ſo fooliſh, that after you haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the ſpirit, you will now end in the fleſh?</p>
               <p>What hath withdrawne you? is it our noueltie that diſliketh you? Can you deſire any greater <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> then a iuſt conformitie of all our Principles with the firſt originall? Would you haue any better preſident, then the paterne of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and the Primitiue Church? What if our ſunne were for a while eclipſed by the interpoſition of Antichriſtian policie? was it therefore no ſunne? What if the good ſeede were ouertopped with tares, that it could hardlie be diſcerned, as in the daies of <hi>Elias</hi> and our Sauiour Chriſt? (the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number diſcountena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing the better part) yet can you not hence inferre, that there was no corne. It is a meere ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Paralogiſme,</hi> to argue <hi>à non videri, ad non eſſe:</hi> as thus; <hi>Eucleo</hi> hath no gold, becauſe no man doth ſee his gold. Man oft taketh his marke amiſſe; it is God
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:4329:53"/> that knoweth who are his. He that hath the fan in his hand, hath now in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time purged his floore, blowne away the chaffe of idolatrous ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and laid the wholeſome graine of his truth on heapes, in the garner of his Church.</p>
               <p>But ſuch hath been his prouidence, in all times, that no age hath been deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of ſome faithfull witneſſe of this faith which we now profeſſe, as doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by thoſe manie anſwers of our learned Proteſtants, to your falſe and friuolous calumniations. I cal them falſe, as being contradicted, euen by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> hiſtorians: I terme them alſo friuolous; for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is it; their names are not regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, therefore there were none vntill <hi>Luthers</hi> time thus affected? Surely moſt abſurd; as if their being did depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other mens writing. <note n="d" place="margin">Multi Papae inuenti ſunt apoſtatae. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co. Lyra in <hi>16.</hi> cap. Mat.</note> Had not <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uester</hi> been a <hi>Necromanticke; Honorius</hi> an hereticall <hi>Monothelite;</hi> and <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> an open <hi>Idolater;</hi> albeit they had ſcaped
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:4329:54"/> the records, and been let ſlip, without the brand of any mans pen? had they not been thus detected to poſteritie, would you therefore ſay, they were not all infected with theſe or thoſe crimes? That which is written may (according to the credit of the author) be ſuppoſed to bee done, but there are manie things done, which (through the iniurie and partialitie of times) are not written at al, which yet a man cannot, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous follie, peremtorilie denie. I ſhall not neede to harpe any longer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſtring, there are ſo many inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be alleaged, as ſome affirme, for <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide,</hi> The way to the true Church. <hi>digr</hi> 48. <hi>pag.</hi> 336. yet vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> 800. yeeres after Chriſt, which may put thoſe that are indifferent, cleane out of doubt, euen of the <hi>viſible ſucceſſion</hi> of our Church; which, were it leſſe appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, were yet no ſuch aduantage to your cauſe as you ſuppoſe.</p>
               <p>Yea but we come ſhort of you in your <hi>Miracles.</hi> Herein alone we yeeld you the bucklers: our whole Church is not able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare (not with <note n="f" place="margin">When hee made his ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Earle of Lece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> 
                  <hi>Leydens,</hi> but) with
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:4329:54"/> 
                  <hi>Louans Lipſius</hi> his little <note n="g" place="margin">Virgo Hal. Antuerp. <hi>1604.</hi> excuſ.</note> pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlet. He lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on ſuch load of our Lady of <hi>Hal,</hi> who hath done ſo many miracles (if her cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion may be credited) that ſhe hath left none in ſtore for them that come after <note n="h" place="margin">Cap. 8. p. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>O quàm variè, &amp; quàm multis in animo, in corpore, in periculis, in calamitatibus, in languoribus, in ipſa morte?</hi> O how manie waies (ſaith he) &amp; to how many perſons hath our Ladie of <hi>Hal</hi> ſtood cloſe at a pinch? Once vpon a time <note n="i" place="margin">Cap. 8. p. 25.</note> a Noblemans <hi>falknor</hi> had either by chance or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence let goe his Lords falcon, which for her extraordinarie high pitch, was a Iewel of high eſteeme. No ſooner was ſhee miſſed, but the poore falkenor is charged to haue made monie of her: with which ſuſpition his Lord was ſo enraged, that he ſwore by no beggars, vnleſſe ſhe were found by ſuch a day, he would make him looke through a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Well, the day came; he could heare no tidings of his hawke: and therefore he heares (that which his maſters intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate choler gaue him cauſe to feare)
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:4329:55"/> euen his owne doome. As he was going to his geare, the executioner being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced, his eies muffled, and now ready to bee turned off the ladder, he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth what a kind wench our feined Ladie of <hi>Hal</hi> was, how good ſhe had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer been at a dead lift; and therefore with heartie ſighes implores her helpe. No ſooner did hee thinke of this bleſſed Ladie, but (marke you me now) the noiſe of a haukes bells began to gingle in the aire; a ſweet melodie, you muſt thinke, to a drooping heart: hee is an earneſt ſutor to haue his face vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, that he might yet once, in his laſt oraiſons, lift vp his eies to heauen: this being accordingly granted, hee dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth his prayers to the ſame Ladies ſhrine, and behold that which is moſt ſtrange, notwithſtanding the multitude of the ſtanders by, the falcon came ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of the aire, and without any lure, did in the ſight of them al, light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſhoulder, who for her eſcape was now tied to a new perch.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:4329:55"/>
               <p>Heere is a miracle of the maker. Do you ſtand amazed? tuſh, this is nothing to what that <hi>Ladie</hi> hath done: ſhe hath <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note> driuen out euill ſpirits; <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 31.</note> aſſwaged ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible tempeſts; <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 28.</note> fetched a child, that was found ſtarke dead, with his heeles vpwards in a muddie ditch: <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi> 33.</note> another that was drowned: <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</note> another that was ſtrangled: <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. <hi>p.</hi> 37.</note> nay a ſtil-borne child, three daies buried, to life againe. I cannot ſtand to tell you how ſhe made <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>John Swickius</hi> loſe the beſt noſe in his face: nor how <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 30. <hi>p.</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>Philip Cluuius</hi> filed his chaines aſunder with an oxe-bone. I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the particular miracles, wherewith <hi>Lipſius</hi> hath canoniſed this ſaint; hee would be angry if you ſhould ſay, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the whetſtone: yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but that he is <hi>ſummus ſimula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di Artifex.</hi> Now if euery one of your Saints had a <hi>Lipſius,</hi> the world would not containe the numberleſſe miracles, that ſhould be then written. But the truth is, we haue too many of theſe alreadie, vnleſſe they were better; and yet I will not ſay, but
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:4329:56"/> that <hi>Lipſius</hi> is worth the reading by the fire-ſide, when men roſte crabs, to driue a man out of a melancholie fit. For I thinke ſobrietie it ſelfe could not chuſe but change countenance to heare him tell theſe ridiculous ieſts ſo ſeriouſlie, as if he did verilie beleeue them to be true. For our parts, wee are not aſhamed to confeſſe, that wee haue no other mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, then thoſe which were wrought by Chriſt, the Prophets, and Apoſtles: of theſe we ſay, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in another ſenſe, <hi>Omnia noſtra ſunt:</hi> they are all ours, being <hi>eiuſdem fidei ſignacula,</hi> ſeals of the verie ſame faith which wee hold. Let thoſe, who haue no other warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for their doctrines, ſeeke to countenance themſelues by impoſition of miracles; it can be no diſparagement to our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that wee come behind you in theſe, wherein we would think it our greateſt ſhame to come neere you.</p>
               <p>We will willinglie giue you leaue to brag of your ſpecious and ſpeculatiue wonders; it is enough for vs to wonder,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:4329:56"/> that ſo many of our late bookes are yet vnanſwered. I do not meane the royall writings of Monarches, too tranſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent for any traiterous fugitiues, or malapert Chaplanes to ſnarle at. I find there are verie many other, which either your pride ſcorneth, or your partialitie ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, or your policie feareth to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: albeit the Biſhop of <hi>Romes</hi> ſlipper hath been lately ſo rent, as it hath no ſound ſole, whereon his triple crowned ſupremacie may tread. This your delay is not without iuſt cauſe: for beſides the diſtruſt you haue in your ſelues, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon an impoſſibility of long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the truth, it doth more neerely concerne you to beſtow ſome time in ending your <note n="ſ" place="margin">Watſons Quodlibets.</note> 
                  <hi>Domestique</hi> differences, and reconciling your <note n="t" place="margin">Bellum Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum.</note> 
                  <hi>obiected</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, then to betake your ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forren controuerſies. As for our <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malists,</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> (as you terme them) howſoeuer they be ſomewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in habite, yet are they vnited in heart, readie at all times to ioyne in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:4329:57"/> againſt any vncircumciſed Philiſtine, that dares conteſt againſt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of their faith. And yet little ſhould they need to ſet their pens about this taske, ſo palpable is the groſeneſſe of your <hi>Theatricall</hi> religion, that, had the eies of all my countrie-men been parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of my little experience, the verie ſight of your abſurd mummeries would, without any learned mans confutation, breed a perpetual and loathing deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in their minds. It is an old ſaying, <hi>Malum non vitatur, niſi cognitum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had I not been an eie-witnes of your idolatrous trumperies, I ſhould not ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionatelie bewaile the eſtate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you are now fallen. I was, I wel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, in my yonger yeares a neere ſeruant vnto a mightie <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Francis</hi> only brother to <hi>Henrie</hi> 3. of France.</p>
                     <p>Records of the Parl. of Paris, about <hi>Salcedo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Prince,</hi> (of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie memorie) whoſe Diademe (had not the <hi>Leaguers</hi> practiſes immaturely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented our hope) would haue been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to none. During which my atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, I was often, vpon <note n="x" place="margin">4. King. 5.19</note> neceſſarie duties, both in field and in Court, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:4329:57"/> ſpectator of thoſe <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rites, to which he was then formerly addicted. Yet, whether it were my parents educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the gouernment of our State, or the wandring humor of youth, I cannot well tell, but well I wot, my conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did more ſuperficiallie ſlide ouer thoſe toies, then of late yeers they haue done. When as being commanded by the King my Maſter, to wait vpon a moſt Noble <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Edward</hi> Earle of <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi> 1605.</note> Perſonage, (whoſe religious, worthie, and bountiful cariage hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched our countrie with his eternall fame) in his embaſſie, to a moſt puiſſant, prudent, &amp; pious <note n="a" place="margin">Arch D.D.</note> 
                  <hi>Princeſſe, (Cuius idaea <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aleſia mihi ſemper ſacra)</hi> I was careful to make that iournie as beneficiall to my experience, as the time would permit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many other occurrences, as the view of the bleeding <hi>VVafer-cake,</hi> &amp;c. I did not omit to informe my iudgement with ſight of many your Maſſes, both priuat and publicke, wherein my eies diſcouered more anticke and iugling trickes, then my eares had euer heard, or
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:4329:58"/> my heart could otherwiſe haue belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. In ſo much that (as two of my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected <note n="b" place="margin">Antony Bright, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Lank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> people, ſtill preſent can yet wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) my eares glowed. Such hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perfumes, as if the Prieſt or his idol had been ſcarce ſweete, ſuch <note n="c" place="margin">Leaue your ducks &amp; your tuckes, &amp; your apiſh to<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, and ſerue God in ſpirit and truth.</note> facings, ſuch knockings, ſuch adorings, yea and ſuch eleuating, as neuer was, nor yet is in the Greeke mother Church, vntil this day.</p>
               <p>I am bold to make my owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence an inducement to bring you (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Countriman) to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that, which otherwiſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of your corrupted affection, you would happilie not ſo carefullie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. I will yet goe one ſtep further, that you may the better perceiue what comfort you are like to find, at your laſt gaſpe, by that religion. That deare Prince my firſt Maſter, (of whom I am glad to make ſo worthie mention) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing been trained from his infancie in the tract of his forefathers, though in ſome <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>For,</hi> Viue la Meſſe.</note> temerarie enterpriſes in his
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:4329:58"/> young yeares (that neuer told thirty) by truſt of his enough aged, but humorous, counſellours, ſeduced, did yet, through the whole courſe of his life, find ſuch weakeneſſe in thoſe grounds, which you now hold, that at his death at <hi>Chater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyerrie,</hi> when there was no longer dally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he would admit neither Prieſt, nor Confeſſor into his preſence, making publicke profeſſion before thoſe that were then preſent, that <hi>he had ſufficientlie confeſſed to God, and that he had placed the whole hope of his ſaluation vpon Jeſus Chriſt the Redeemer and Sauiour of the world.</hi> The like did that thrice-excellent and renowned Princeſſe, (now in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) <hi>Marie Queene of Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wager of France,</hi> make at her laſt end, that <hi>She hoped to be ſaued by the merits of Christ alone.</hi> And if preſent Agents of Princes may be credited, it was euen ſo with that ouer-blindly deuout <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. whom your diabolicall Friar, for the poore Kings loue to Friars, maſſacred, I will not ſay, martyrized. This was alſo the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:4329:59"/> of <hi>Stephen Gardener</hi> (a man of <note n="e" place="margin">Nephew to a Queene of <hi>England,</hi> and Coſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to a King <hi>à latre.</hi>
                  </note> higher deſcent, then commonlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a reuerend Biſhop told him that he muſt look to be ſaued by Chriſt alone: Yea my Lord, quoth he, it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede; but if you open that gap to the people, it will goe wrong with the Church. Long were the three forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Worthies grounded in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſchoole, and of as deepe iudgement, as moſt of their Anceſtors; and yet you ſee when they had caſt vp all their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, there was neither <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> nor works of ſupererogation would doe any good; the <hi>ſumma totalis</hi> in their bookes was <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> As for all other your ſuperſtitious traſh, it will be as the morning deaw, in the heate of that laſt conflict; all your other helpes and hopes will bee blowne away like a ſpiders webbe.</p>
               <p>Now, were it not an <hi>indecorum</hi> to deſcend from a conſideration of ſo great moment; which (if your heart bee not ſealed, I ſhould ſay, ſeared, with a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:4329:59"/> hot iron, out of Satans forge) cannot but bee very forceable in your relenting thoughts? I would alſo willinglie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you, what ſmall encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are like to attend your temporall life. And the rather, becauſe it was this <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> which led you into thoſe bogs, wherein you are now bemired. What your entertainment hath hitherto been, I find <note n="f" place="margin">Pag. 96.</note> you haue no great cauſe to make any great boaſt. What it will be in theſe daies of peace, your grand Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents wanting worke for themſelues, you may eaſilie iudge. Policie will teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to repoſe too much truſt in him, who <note n="g" place="margin">Proditionem, non Proditore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> hath defiled his owne neſt: Common ſenſe will informe them, that he, whom miſerie hath drawne to them, will ſerue them the like ſlipperie tricke, and by equiualent diſcontents be ſoone driuen from them: Reaſon likewiſe may tell you, they will neuer hold him a fit Churchman, whom they know to bee a <note n="h" place="margin">Vir vxorius.</note> womans ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Were there no other rub but this, yet mee thinks your mariage
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:4329:60"/> ſhould lay an impoſſibilitie to the charge of your groundleſſe hopes. Did I ſay your marriage? nay your experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which can informe you of few or none of your <hi>Apostaticall</hi> forerunners, whoſe age did reape the harueſt, which their youthfull yeeres had ſowne. After they had once ſerued <note n="i" place="margin">Spem pretio non emas.</note> 
                  <hi>Antichrists</hi> turne, to ſtop their mouthes, from any cofer-demaunds, they were ſet in the forefront of the battell, as mercenarie ſouldiers, and kept at ſuch a bay, as that Tyrants vaſſals, who, at euery beck, tumbled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues downe from the top of a tower, to ſhew their obedience. You muſt haue more skil then your predeceſſors, if you will fetch ſweet water out of ſo ſalt a ſea, or grapes from thornes, or figges from ſuch thiſtles. You may flatter your ſelfe as you pleaſe, but <hi>Res tibi ad Reſtim redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit planiſſimè:</hi> In ſtead of a Prelate of their Church, they will make you a martyr in their red <note n="l" place="margin">Non equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem inuideo.</note> Kalender. Thus ſhall you be faine to cloſe vp a miſerable life, with a deſpicable and diſmall end.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:4329:60"/>
               <p>My earneſt and hearty deſire of your recouery, from this your <hi>Lethargie,</hi> hath made me ſomewhat more prolixe, then the bounds of a letter will well endure The ſhort is, I haue caſt my pen as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togenes</hi> did his pencell: If it hath fallen right, it is well; howſoeuer, I am <note n="m" place="margin">Inuitum qui ſeruat, idem facit occidenti</note> reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute. My ſcope hath been to put you in remembrance, from <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
                  <hi>whence,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi> 
                  <hi>whither,</hi> and <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 
                  <hi>how you are fallen:</hi> ſo that you may repent, and doe the <hi>firſt workes.</hi> Your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in time reclaimed will be veniall: your obſtinacie will not onely bee dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, but damnable, if <note n="n" place="margin">Errare hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerare diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum.</note> perpetuall. That you haue fallen, the truth attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes it to your outward grieuances: That you returne, it will be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to come from your inward, and more deliberate iudgement. Neither will we doubt, but that the broken bone being well ſet, will bee much ſtronger then before. It is now in your owne choice, whether you will be <note n="o" place="margin">Si quis curet opem ferre, &amp; dimittere fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uem, non vis ſeruari?</note> healed or no. Now is the time either to raiſe, or ruinate not onelie your fortunes, but
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:4329:61"/> euen the finall eſtate, both of bodie and ſoule. The benefit you may (perhaps) bring to your Countrie, by the diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of that which your trauel hath made knowne vnto you, may make ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for your former reuolt: vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your true and loyall ſubmiſſion, I am in good hope his Maieſtie will reach out the ſcepter of his mercy, vnto which his roiall nature is ſo inclinable, that his Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> hath (in my owne knowledge) bin ſundrie times an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and earneſt Petitioner, to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the actuall execution of thoſe neceſſarie lawes, which were enacted long before he was inueſted in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Crowne, againſt malefactors of this nature.</p>
               <p>You thinke, I am ſure, your pen was very prodigall, in wiſhing him the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of <note n="p" place="margin">Pag. 51.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> but let me ſpeak it without flatterie, (from which I was euer knowne to be naturally eſtranged) whether you reſpect the gifts of nature or grace; the quicknes of apprehenſion;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:4329:61"/> the deepeneſſe of iudgement; the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of affections; the weight of well ſeaſoned ſpeech, in common diſcourſe, and ſcholaſticall diſpute; the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of State; or the fatherly care in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the good of the Church; he is, if not many degrees before, yet not one iot behind that worthie <hi>Constantine:</hi> whoſe either politike neglect, or fatall miſfortune was ſuch, that he was not i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated in that <note n="q" place="margin">Euſeb. de vit. Const. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>62.</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. Eccl. hist. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> holy Sacrament of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> vntil a very little before his death. And I am verily perſwaded, that in the matter of faith, wherein you deſire a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel imitation, he is ſo farre from lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Constantine,</hi> that he is able in ſingle conference to grauell his beſt <hi>B B.</hi> were they now aliue to be his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites; and therefore not to take pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of any of the weaker ſex, with whom you couertlie vpbraide him. It is not my meaning to enlarge the liſts of this compariſon any further: that which I would haue you know is this, that as he is the vicegerent of the great King,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:4329:62"/> ſo is his throne ſupported as well by the pillar of <note n="r" place="margin">Dolet, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties cogitur eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſerox.</note> Mercy, as of Iuſtice. I ſpeake not this to hire your returne, (God bee thanked) our land hauing great plentie of more skilfull warriers, who dailie fight the Lords battell; nor that we feare the venome of your poiſonous pen, which will bee ſoone beaten backe into your owne bowels; but that your ſoule may not periſh in the day of the Lord: when (if you thus perſiſt) the inexpia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble crimes of blaſpheming the true faith, and drawing others into the ſame ſnare of death, will be more heauie, then millions of milſtones about your neck. Which fearefull iudgement, that by timelie reconciliation you may eſcape, theſe haſtie lines ſhall bee ſeconded with my hearty Prayers. From <hi>Queeneburrow</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Festo S. Philip. &amp; Jacobi.</hi> 1609.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edward Hoby.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:62"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S J had neere ended the Printing of the two former Letters, J re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a third from Sir <hi>Edward Hoby</hi> (the originall now remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with himſelfe) directed vnto him from the father of the ſaid <hi>T. H.</hi> which he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to inſert, for the better ſatisfaction of any vnpreiudicate Reader.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Pag. 32. lin. 15. reade, turned vp. pag. 47. lin. 9. reade, <hi>Forſan aut deſunt,</hi> &amp;c. which is more aduantagious. pag. 70. lin. 21. reade, <hi>as much as he.</hi> pag. 71. lin. vlt. reade, <hi>mortuorum</hi>)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter_to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:63"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:63"/>
            <head>TO THE HON. SIR EDWARD HOBY Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may pleaſe you to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed, that my vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſonne <hi>Theophilus Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons</hi> (within ſome foure yeares, or thereabouts, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was Maſter of Arts) would needs forgoe the Vniuerſity, to go with my Lord of <hi>London,</hi> that now is, being then Elect Biſhop of <hi>Glocester.</hi> And in regard of his yong yeares, I thought it verie vnfit; perſwaded him, and commanded him to ſtay in the houſe, till he were better read in Diuinitie, and his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein, &amp; in other things, better rectified, which I found to be verie defectiue. My Lord, for his part, very honorably told me, that he had perſwaded him thereto, and would be as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to do him good, as if his time were ſpent in his houſe, and after ſome two or three yeares would receiue him. No perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s might ſerue,
<pb facs="tcp:4329:64"/> but he importuned my Lord; ſo as from <hi>Oxford</hi> he went: though I had told him before M. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Schoole-maſter of <hi>Westminster,</hi> and M. <hi>Iles</hi> the Proctor, that (if he would not be ruled by me, and ſtay at <hi>Oxford</hi>) my hope of his well doing was at an end. When he had been leſſe then two yeares with my Lord of <hi>London,</hi> (then Biſhop of <hi>Glocester</hi>) hee withdrew himſelfe from his Lordſhip, and made ſuite for the Lecture at S. <hi>Dunstons:</hi> which I hearing of, perſwaded him from, by my letters, in the beſt manner I could, for the reaſons afore mentioned, and the rather, becauſe I knew the Auditorie there to be verie learned and iudicious: no perſwaſion might draw him backe to his Lord and Maſter, though his Lordſhip wrote diuers letters to him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call him to his place.</p>
            <p>Afterwards a friend of mine told me, that he thought he was in hand to marrie: whereupon I wrote vnto him what I heard, and my counſel, aduice, and charge withall. His anſwere by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was, that he was abuſed by the reporter, and proteſted that as he deſired Gods bleſſing and mine, he neuer would marrie with any woman, before I had knowledge of his liking that way, and ſhould giue approbation thereto: this was about Michaelmas, and he was maried in a clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine manner before Chriſtmas following, whereof I neuer knew till after Midſommer terme following: and he vnderſtanding that I had knowledge of it, and much grieued thereat,
<pb facs="tcp:4329:64"/> eloyned himſelfe from his wife, and kept in the North-parts till neere Hollontide. When he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>London</hi> (but not to his wife) there he publiſhed a ſmall booke in print, flatly againſt the abſurdities he now ſo ſtrongly ſeemeth to maintaine: and within twentie daies after, at the moſt, got him beyond the Seas, leauing his wife in great diſtreſſe, ſorow and griefe. Before his going he borrowed diuers ſummes of money, with purpoſe (I am perſwaded) neuer to repay them: and amongſt the reſt, abuſed my ſelfe for ten pound. In May laſt paſt, I trauelled to Saint <hi>Omers,</hi> with a good friend of mine, to ſeeke him out: where finding him, I laboured earneſtly to bring him backe with me, aſſured him of ſafetie, &amp;c. He promiſed, ſwore and proteſted his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after me to my Lord of <hi>London,</hi> within three weekes after my comming away; though I thinke he neuer meant it. Being in S. <hi>Omers,</hi> I willed and charged him, not to reueale my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there; notwithſtanding he made it knowne the ſame night to a Popiſh Prieſt, as vpon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination he confeſſed to me the next morning: which made vs preſently to come away, fearing our liues to be in danger amongſt ſuch a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of helhounds, as that towne is ſtuffed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Sir, I aſſure my ſelfe, and all men that well knew him may be perſwaded, that his Poperie came from the diſcontentment, by his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie mariage, wherin he dealt ſo perfidiouſly; and ſo it hath pleaſed God to puniſh that ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:4329:65"/> with many other ſins. How carefully I brought him vp, and what meanes I vſed for his trayning vp in the truth of religion, and in good inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of manners, God knoweth, and the world can witnes with me. If I had had abilitie to haue anſwered his leaud booke, I would gladly and ſpeedily haue vndertaken it; but I am glad that one ſo Honorable, learned, worthie and wiſe, hath vouchſafed it. For my hope is, that the whole rabble of Papiſts ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo much, by you, of the cauſe of his comming to their hotchpotch religion, that they will be aſhamed any longer to patronize him, if they be not paſt all ſhame.</p>
            <p>So hauing troubled your Worſhip with a long, tedious relation, which commeth from a grieued heart (and the rather for that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie yong mans courſes haue occaſioned the death of his louing mother, my late deare wife) I craue pardon, and leaue the man and the matter to your wiſedome, cenſure, and pleaſure, and will euer reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to be commanded, <hi>ROBERT HIGGONS.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Chilton,</hi> 
                  <date>28. <hi>May.</hi> 1609.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4329:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
